<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A new mystery in physick discovered by curing of fevers &amp; agues by quinquina or Jesvites powder translated from the French by Dr. Belon, with additions.</title>
            <title>Traité de la guérison des fièvres par le quinquina. English</title>
            <author>Monginot, François, fl. 1679.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 125KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 86 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51140</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12323092</idno>
  <idno type="VID">59497</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240990543</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2416</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32103</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12323092</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51140)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59497)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1017:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A new mystery in physick discovered by curing of fevers &amp; agues by quinquina or Jesvites powder translated from the French by Dr. Belon, with additions.</title>
                  <title>Traité de la guérison des fièvres par le quinquina. English</title>
                  <author>Monginot, François, fl. 1679.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[60], 99 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Will. Crook ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A translation of his Traité de la guérison des fièvres par le quinuina."--NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Monginot by Wing and NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Quinine --  Therapeutic use.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59497:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A New Mystery</hi> IN PHYSICK DISCOVERED, By curing of <hi>Fevers</hi> &amp; <hi>Agues</hi> BY Quinquina OR <hi>JESƲITES POWDER.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Translated from the <hi>French,</hi> by Dr. <hi>Belon,</hi> with Additions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Will. Crook</hi> at the <hi>Green Dragon</hi> without <hi>Temple Barr.</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="addendum">
            <pb facs="tcp:59497:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59497:2"/>
            <head>The way how to use the Bark for an Ague; Translated out of <hi>Itali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> Printed at <hi>Rome</hi> above Four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>score Years ago; added to this, by Dr. <hi>M.</hi> Fellow of the Colledge of Physitians <hi>London,</hi> who had it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove twenty Years by him.</head>
            <p>THis Bark is brought from the Kingdom of <hi>Peru,</hi> and is called <hi>China, alias</hi> for the Ague; which is made use of for a <hi>Quartain</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue, and a <hi>Tertian</hi> that comes with a cold Shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering: It is used as followeth:</p>
            <p>Take two Drams thereof, pound it very small, then sift it through a fine Searse, and about three hours before the Fit is expected to come; steep it in a Glass of good strong White-wine; and when the cold Fit begins to come, or the least inkling of it be perceived, take the whole Dose so prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and let the Patient betake himself to his Bed. Take notice, that the Bark may be given (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:59497:3"/>mentioned) in a <hi>Tertian</hi> Ague, when it is fix'd and habitual for many days.</p>
            <p>Moreover, you may give of the Bark (as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-mentioned) in an Ague, that comes every day with a cold Fit, and that after its Declina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Patient sleep in Bed; and this ought not to be given, but when twenty five or thirty Days are past, as Physitians shall think most ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient.</p>
            <p>Constant Experience testifieth, that it hath cured almost all those who have taken of it; the Body first having been well purged, and for four days after having taken no Physick whatsoever: but it is to be observed, that this is not to be given, but by the Approbation of Able Physitians, that they may judge when it is a proper and convenient time to take it.</p>
            <p>Take notice, that it is not necessary to make a new and strong Purgation for the taking of the Bark, having already done it upon the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion of the Distemper. It will suffice only the precedent day, to have had some Evacua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Body, with some light thing, or a Clyster.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="translators_preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:59497:3"/>
            <head>AN <hi>INTRODƲCTION</hi> TO THE French Author, <hi>By the Translator.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>GOodness is as diffusive as Light, and it is the Opinion of some good Men, that they are no longer fit to live in the world, than while they can do good. The great Christian Philosopher points at that Lesson, when, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Notion of Charity, he recommends unto us a Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicative
<pb facs="tcp:59497:4"/>Goodness to attend us in all our Actions. Had I not been inform'd of this Duty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forehand, the good Example of the Worthy Author of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tise on the <hi>Quinquina,</hi> had suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently instructed me therein. It is in Imitation of him therefore, that I have presented the Publick with my Observations and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod in the use of this <hi>Peruvian</hi> Bark that he treats of, which he calls the <hi>Quinquina,</hi> and that ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally goes under the Notion of the <hi>Jesuits Powder;</hi> not with the least Design of Contradiction or Opposition, to that which he has so judiciously, and with so much Judgment writ. But to inform the Reader, that besides the <hi>Peruvian</hi> Bark, Nature has provided other Remedies against
<pb facs="tcp:59497:4"/>all sorts of Fevers and Agues; such as, besides my own Experirience, have been found, and approv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of by divers Learned and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Physitians, to be not only Specificks against all preterna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Ferments and Obstructions; but that through their powerful Vertue, and great Energy, in pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying the Blood, freeing the Spirits from all Heterogenious Qualities, and fortifying of all the Noble and Principal Parts of the Body, have most deservedly acquired the Names of Renova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and Preservers of Health.</p>
            <p>And of truth, I have seen that through the Use of the hereafter-mention'd febrifuge, compounded extract, when giv'n against Agues and Fevers, unto such Persons as were besides, of very ill habit of
<pb facs="tcp:59497:5"/>Bodies, that had been advertised and threatned, both by such In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal and External Symptoms, as sufficiently did inform them (as well as those Physitians with whom they communicated) of the approach of dangerous Diseases and Distempers, those Persons have been strangely rescued from the Tyranny of those Diseases, at the same time as they were freed from their Fevers; of which some were so short, that at the second or third Fit at most, they were released: so that it could not be expected, that the Fermentative Heat of the Fever, could have contributed towards the remov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the other Causes of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stempers; much less, that it could have cured those Persons; but that they were recovered through
<pb facs="tcp:59497:5"/>the renewing, and preservative Qualities of the Febrifuge Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract.</p>
            <p>But I know, that there are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Persons that will not admit of such things as Preservers and Renewers; and that are of Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that God has provided Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies only for the Cure of Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eases; but none to prevent their Generation, and to enable our Nature to oppose and resist their first Approaches; and even to intercept them in their Embrio, and before they could be rang'd under the <hi>Classis</hi> of any Distem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers: Therefore I will in few words give my Opinion thereon, and then discover those things, through whose Uses I have seen surprising Effects.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:59497:6"/>
            <p>Doubtless, but that Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mense Goodness, which has or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained Remedies for the Cure of Humane Bodies, has provided some also for the Preservation and Prolongation of Health: For if that Dead Bodies (as Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience does daily teach us) such as are wholly depriv'd of assist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Qualities, are so preserv'd, through the Vertues of some par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Medicaments, as to be kept from Putrefaction for many after Ages; why may there not be expected such, or rather a far greater Advantage, from some Medicaments, when administred to Living Bodies, that are reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished with Vital Spirits, and with a Balsom of Life?</p>
            <p>It is the Opinion of the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that our Nature cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new
<pb facs="tcp:59497:6"/>it self, without the concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Aid of some Powerful Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicament, by reason of her Insuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency in the Separation and Extraction of a clear, pure, and genuine Quintessence, from Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, through which she might be rendred capable (without any Foreign Aid or Assistance) daily to renew her self, and be conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with a small Pittance, in lieu of that large Proportion of Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which she daily requires; by which, many Impurities are dispers'd throughout the whole Body by the Circulation of the Blood, which Defect puts it into a Continual Labour for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelling of them.</p>
            <p>Thus its daily Deficiency is frequently manifested by its too frequent Alterations into divers
<pb facs="tcp:59497:7"/>sorts of Distempers: For could she extract any such Excellency from her Aliments, Life would then be a Continual Series of Health without Alteration.</p>
            <p>But seeing our Nature is desti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of such Qualities, being too much vitiated and perverted, to attain to that height of Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by her peculiar Fire, and the other Instruments of her own Elaboratory, Medicine must be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited to lend her an Aid, by refined and spirituous Medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, to procure Preservation: For our Nature being thus assist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the Sphere of her Activity will be extended beyond its Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Bounds, both for our Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation and Renovation.</p>
            <p>This is further verified in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers things, which acquire a lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
<pb facs="tcp:59497:7"/>Duration, by curious and advantageous Peparations and Mixtures. Thus Wine distill'd into a Spirit, is kept incorrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, though apt to evaporate; and by mixing of it with some of its own Flegm, both are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served, and longer kept, than when separated; so our weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened, or debillitated Liquor of Life, being impregnated with Spirituous and Balsamick Essen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, have more Force and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue.</p>
            <p>In the Chymical Anatomy of Blood, the fix'd Salt is found in very small Quantity in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of the Volatil; which fix'd Salt is a most powerful Principle, whose Balsamick Parts are so absolutely necessary to Life, that the Duration thereof is to
<pb facs="tcp:59497:8"/>be limited by the quantity and quality of the said Salt.</p>
            <p>Now, whereas the Heart, first Agent of the Blood, extracts but a small Proportion of this fix'd Salt out of Nutriments, to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply plentifully, and distribut<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> to all the parts of the Body, and that the Volatil is very apt to e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vaporate and dissipate, whereby the parts are continually cravin<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> for a Supply: If that any Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy be found in Natures Family that can add Energy to the fix'd Salt, and suppress the too subti<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Evaporation of the Volatil; o<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> necessity then, Preservation an<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Renovation may be adjudged in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible.</p>
            <p>For it is evident, that the mor<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> any Mixture abounds with fix'<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Salt, the longer it lasts, and live
<pb facs="tcp:59497:8"/>the longer, and with less Propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Aliments. This we do not only see in Innate things, but in Animals also; as in Vipers, out of whose Flesh, a very conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable quantity of fix'd Salt may be extracted.</p>
            <p>All this is said without dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating from that Ferment Spirit, the Prince of Life, who assisted with its Balsom, concurring with the Result of some exterior resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative Principles, does visit, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten, and cherish all the parts, and makes them participant of all its Qualities.</p>
            <p>These Premisses considered, to doubt of the Virtues of Remedies for Conservation and Renovati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Health, is directly to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose Experience, verified by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, and confirmed by divers Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb facs="tcp:59497:9"/>and Modern Authentick Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors.</p>
            <p>But the ways and means to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain unto these Preservers? <hi>Hic labor, hoc opus.</hi> To this purpose, Man, who naturally aspires to Glory, wants but Diligence to search, with Courage to effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, seeing that he is already en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with Reason, to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand, that he is in Possession of that Instrument of Instruments, the Hand, to operate, and that kind and plentiful Nature sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies him with all requisite Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials, profusively spreading her Treasures at his Feet, only im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploring the Ingenious Artist's Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence.</p>
            <p>For, <hi>Ʋbi Natura desinit, ibi in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipit Chimicus.</hi> None can err, (at least beyond Redress) that
<pb facs="tcp:59497:9"/>will with Care and Circumspe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, follow the Steps of so wise a Mistress. Let but the Artist observe her Ways and Method in Generation and Production, and they will easily guide him unto the Destruction of the same Natural Product; by which means, they being laid open, and their constitutive Parts or Principles separated, the Artist will easily discern what parts are for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novation and Preservation, from those that are offensive to Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Bodies.</p>
            <p>But before I proceed to the Examination of such Principles, as are proper to preserve Health, it will be requisie to give an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of those things that are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structive to Health: To that purpose, I need but to refer the
<pb facs="tcp:59497:10"/>Reader unto that part of the Book, in which the Author does very judiciously treat of the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bifick Cause of Fevers and Agues. There you will find, that Acides are the Principles of preternatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Fermentations, and of all Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions, as well as of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viation of the Functions of the Stomach, of Chilification, of Sanguification, and consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of all those things that are destructive to Health.</p>
            <p>This being observ'd, we may now come to the examining of what is of a nature proper to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy those Acides, either by Precipitation, Dulcification, or Expulsion. But this likewise has been touch'd upon by our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, though not so fully as might have been; perhaps, not
<pb facs="tcp:59497:10"/>to swell the Book beyond those Limits which he first designed it: For it might have been said, and not unnecessarily proved, that there are divers sorts of Acides, from whence proceed those vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous sorts of evil Fermentations, which produce the variety of Fevers. As it may be found by the Actions of those Acides or Alkalies: For it is observ'd, that whereas all the greatest part of Common <hi>Menstruums</hi> or Dissol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents are Acide and Corrosive, especially those that are used on Minerals and Mettals; yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst them, some will dissolve one mix'd, while they will not touch any other, which will with ease be dissolved by another A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide, much less stronger than the former.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:59497:11"/>
            <p>Now this Variety of Acides, I judge, may be the Cause that Fevers are not always certainly cured, nor without being subject to Returns; because that though the <hi>Jesuits Powder,</hi> or <hi>Peruvian</hi> Bark, is endowed with such Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, as are of Power, frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to cure Fevers, and sometimes even at the very first Dose; yet it may be composed of such parts, amongst which, some may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease one sort of Acide, while that its other parts destroys o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Acides: or if this will not be allowed of, yet there may be, and it is very propable, that there are some Acides, that will not in the least be altered by its Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Efficacy, though that they may be sometimes in so small a proportion in our Bodies, that
<pb facs="tcp:59497:11"/>the Remedy having overcome the other Acides, Nature, by her own Strength and Vigor, being only assisted by some fit Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, will expell that small porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a remaining Acide, and free it self from that inconsiderable Enemy.</p>
            <p>Therefore it is requisite, that a Search be made amongst the rest of Nature's Products, for some other Specificks, that may be as powerful to subdue those other Acides, as the <hi>Quinquina</hi> is in overcoming some.</p>
            <p>To this purpose we must have Recourse unto Chymistry, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with to examine the particular parts of Mixts, in order to make Choice of such as are proper to that Effect; and not only capable of destroying such Acides, but
<pb facs="tcp:59497:11"/>of Power also, to prevent their Generation, and that consequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are not only Remedies against Fevers, but Preservers and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newers of Health also.</p>
            <p>Amongst divers others of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture's Children, I have made some Experimental Observations on some, out of the Three Natural Families of Minerals, Vegetables and Animals: In the Mineral Kingdom, I have found <hi>Antimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, Allum,</hi> and <hi>Coral,</hi> to be most powerful Dulcifers, Precipitaters, and Expulsers of divers sorts of Acides. Amongst Metalls, which are the most perfect of the Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Production, I have met with Mercury, with Lead; but above all, with Gold, to the same ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, but much more powerfully, when mixed with the <hi>Jesuits
<pb facs="tcp:59497:12"/>Powder,</hi> after a due Preparation, than either of them by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves. Of truth, Gold, when thoroughly opened and dissol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, has a great Corresponden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy with the <hi>Peruvian</hi> Bark, as to its Color, its Odor, and its Taste: For, whereas Gold before its Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, has neither Taste nor Odor, and that it preserves its Native Glorious Lustre: It is no sooner prepared by the Hand of an expert Artist, but that it becomes acerb, restrictive, bitter, of an austere Smell and Taste, and yielding a deep Red Color; all which Qualities are remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in the right <hi>Quinquina:</hi> And consequently, Gold may be said to have in it all those first Qualities that are in the <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quina,</hi> which endows it with that
<pb facs="tcp:59497:13"/>Power and Vertue, against all evil Fermentations, besides its Cordial Vertue.</p>
            <p>Amongst the Vegetables, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides the <hi>Quinquina,</hi> I have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serv'd, that Tartar, Opium, and the little Centaury, have some particulat Prevalency over some sorts of Acides likewise.</p>
            <p>And in the Number of Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals, I have seen wonderful Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects by the Use of Vipers, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d of, the Salt of Wine, or Sal Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniac.</p>
            <p>But all those Advantages, with which Nature has endowed these Remedies, are not to be expected, except they be first carefully prepared, and divested from some unnecessary Parts, before you can come to enjoy those that are of Power to combat the evil
<pb facs="tcp:59497:13"/>Ferments, to destroy the Fevers which are their Results, and to preserve and renovate.</p>
            <p>To this purpose, we must fly again to Chymistry for Succor: It is it which must fit us with such Vehicles, out of which no Acides can be extracted for the Reception of the Tinctures of all those fore-mentioned Mixts.</p>
            <p>For, to give any Acides in order to destroy Acides, cannot be a true Method; at least, those Acides, which are natural to those Mixts, which are employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, must of necessity impede the other parts from operating with that vigor and energy upon the Acides, that they would do, were they not in some measure kept back and dull'd, by the Conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Acides or other Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hicles.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:59497:14"/>
            <p>Therefore Wines, Beers, Ales, Juices, or any other Liquors that are acide, or out of which an Acide can be drawn by Distilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, are not so proper to receive the Tincture of those Medica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, nor to be administred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to those Bodies that are affected with any of the above-named Causes of Distempers; as those Vehicles that have no Acide in them.</p>
            <p>We must then seek after such Menstruums or Dissolvents, as are wholly divested from all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Acidity. But where are these Liquors to be found? E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven every where, both Natural and Artificial.</p>
            <p>Now to be free with the World, and not to lap up my Talent in a Napkin, and bury it under
<pb facs="tcp:59497:14"/>Ground, I will openly declare what those Vehicles are, and lay down the Proportion of those Mixtures and their Menstruums, by which I hope to exempt my self from the Number of those that make Mysteries of all their Remedies, though no better than those of others, more for their own Profit, than the Good of the Publick.</p>
            <p>And to begin, <hi>May</hi> Dew, and Common Spring Water, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Addition whatsoever, will open Coral, which for its hardness, I have placed amongst the Minerals. And no wonder, if once we seriously consider, that it is a maritime Plant, which is soft in the Water, while it grows, but which hardens, when it is loosened from its Root, when it
<pb facs="tcp:59497:15"/>is decayed under Water, or when it is exposed to the open Air.</p>
            <p>The way to open Coral with Common Water, so as to make it yield a Blood-red Tincture, is as follows.</p>
            <p>Take of good red Coral, as much as you please, make it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a gross Powder, in a Marble Mortar; set it in a Glass Vess<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l, poure over it as much Spring Water as will bring it all into the Consistance of a thin Paste or Pap, with stirring them well to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with a Wooden Spatula, so long as you will see any Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fervescency to appear; set it to a very moderate Heat to digest, until the Water be almost all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaporated: Moisten the Coral as before, with more Water, stir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with the Spatula, and set
<pb facs="tcp:59497:15"/>it in Digestion, as before, till it be almost quite dried: Thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat humecting, digesting and defecating, during eight or ten days; then set it dry in a Glass Retort, to an open Fire; to which add a Receiver well clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed; distil, siltrate the Liquor that is in the Receiver; then set it in a Matrass, or Glass Bolts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, and let it sublime with a convenient Fire, till all the Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latil Salt be separated; set the remaining Liquor in a small Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; to which, add of the Spirit of Wine, to the Eminency of three Fingers breadth: Let all digest together; then distil it to the Consistency of Hony; poure over it of Common Spring Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: Let it digest and gently boil, until all the Empierume, or
<pb facs="tcp:59497:16"/>Smell of Burning be gone; then let the Water be all evaporated; pour over the remaining Matter, of Spirit of Wine, accuated with the Essential Salt of Tartar, to the Eminency of three Fingers breadth; then after some little Digestion, distill off the Spirit of Wine, and in the Body will remain the red Tincture of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, deprived of all Acidity, which is a great Dulcifer of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cides, opener of Obstructions, and resister of Putrefaction, and therefore very proper to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the Tincture of the <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quina</hi> in <hi>putride,</hi> and malignant Fevers.</p>
            <p>With Common Water may be also extracted the Tinctures of the <hi>Quinquina,</hi> that of the Little Centaury; and if you please, that
<pb facs="tcp:59497:16"/>of <hi>Opium</hi> also; adding, for the quicker dispatch, a small Propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of some Alkaly, as the Salt of Tartar, or the like: all which Extractions are so easy and plain to be performed, that I shall not have need to set them down here. Thus much as to the Natural Menstruum without Acides. I shall now give you the Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Allum,</hi> which is made with the same Menstruum also: After which, I shall treat of the Artificial Dissolvent without A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cides, by which, Mercury, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timony, Lead, Salt, of Tartar, Sal Armoniac, are prepared and opened.</p>
            <p>But before I come to the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of Allum, take this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Account of its Qualities and Vertues.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:59497:17"/>
            <p>Allum has its Principles, which are a Flegm, an Acidity, a white Earth, out of which being dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved in its own Acide, the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terogenious parts may be separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, and there will remain a Salt. This Allum will not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit any thing to putrifie: It will prevent the Progress of a Gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grene; and by the use of it, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Members have been preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from Amputation, when they were tending to Mortification. It is excellent to preserve the tone of the Ventricle or Stomach: It is a most powerful Clarifier, which may be seen in the Use of Whey, in the clarifying of Hony, so suddainly and perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that divers Filtrations would not do the like: It is excellent against all Fluxes, Spitting of
<pb facs="tcp:59497:17"/>Blood, Defluxions, and a great Provoker of Urines; It extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guishes the violent Heat of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers and Thirst.</p>
            <p>These are the Qualities and Vertues of Allum, by which you may guess of its Power in Fevers and Agues. Now I come to its Preparation, which is thus:</p>
            <p>Take of Roch-Allum, as much as you please, make it into fine Powder, set it in a Glass Body, joyn to it an Head, draw off the Flegm, cohobate so often, till it be drunk up: Or, if you would go a better way to work, dissolve what proportion you please of Roch-Allum, in clear Spring Water, circulate this Dissolution during fifteen Days, let the Ves<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel cool, then separate from the Liquor that which is congealed,
<pb facs="tcp:59497:18"/>evaporate the Solution with a gentle Fire, take the congealed Allum, remaining in the Bottom in a fine Powder, set it in a cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culating Vessel, with distille<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Common Water, to the heigh<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> of two Fingers breadth abov<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the Matter; stir or agitate the<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> together, the sooner to dissolv<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the Allum. The Water will tur<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> to a Milky whiteness; circulat<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> all, during a Month, in a clos<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> luted Vessel, agitate the Vesse<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> once in three or four days, afte<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> which, open the Vessel and the<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> separate the clear Water fro<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the congealed Allum, which co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>agulates in Heat; set the Wate<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> in a cold place, in a Glass Bod<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> within eight Days, you will fin<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> a congealed Substance in th<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Bottom of the Vessel; separat<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:59497:18"/>from it the remaining Liquor, by Inclination, and set it to congeal again, as before, into a Substance as clear as Chrystal; separate the Liquor again, by inclination, and set it to congeal, as before, in a cold place.</p>
            <p>These three coagulated Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances, different in Color, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistency and Taste, make all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one Powder together, which dissolve with Common Distilled Water, in a large circulating Ves<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel, well luted, and set in a cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culating Heat, <hi>in balneo,</hi> during two Months, and all will be changed into a most pleasant Sweetness, admirable in all Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, and internal Inflammations of the <hi>Viscera;</hi> not by a suddain Precipitation of the Acides; but by commixing with them, and
<pb facs="tcp:59497:19"/>dulcifying of them: Thus much of Allum, and of its Use in Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers.</p>
            <p>I have already said, that in order to destroy Acides, other Acides are not to be used; but that in lieu of them, <hi>Alcalies</hi> and other Sweetners should be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed: Therefore I shall now only give you a short Account of a particular Vehicle, not only for Minerals, but for Mettals al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, amongst which, Gold it self, though so difficult in yielding its Tincture, but by Corrosives, shall not be excepted.</p>
            <p>Take as much as you please of Salt of Tartar, imbrue it with distilled Vinegar, distill it; when that the Acide arises, cease the Distillation; pour over it of the best Spirit of Wine, rectified
<pb facs="tcp:59497:19"/>with Pot-ashes, as much as will dissolve the embrued Salt, (observing, that just so much, and no more of the Salt, than was at first dissolved in the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar, will be dissolved in the Spirit of Wine) distill as before, there will first come over something that is muddy and stinking, which, cast away; pour new Spirit of Wine on the Matter, and distill, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; repeat this, until that you see like unto black Grapes to appear in the Glass; pour on Spirit of Wine, distill again; then will appear white, and shining Grapes; cohobate the same Spirit again, with some such Addition of New; and then will appear a Substance like unto Talk, continue this
<pb facs="tcp:59497:20"/>Operation, till that all be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted into a Talk, or into a Leafy Earth, which is the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est opener of Obstructions in the World; to which, add a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain as much of the former Spirit of Wine, as will dissolve it all into a Liquor.</p>
            <p>Thus you have the Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Tartar, and the Alca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lised Vehicle, in one and the same preparation.</p>
            <p>Now with this Menstruum or Vehicle, Mercury may in this manner be prepared.</p>
            <p>Take as much as you please of <hi>Mercurius dulcis,</hi> make it into a very fine Powder; set it in a small Circulating Ves<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel,
<pb facs="tcp:59497:20"/>pour over it of this Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sential Salt of Tartar, dissolv'd in Spirit of Wine, as much as will cover it the breadth of three Fingers; set it to digest and circulate in a gentle Heat, during Forty Days after which, open the Vessel, and in the Bottom, you will find the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury in a very fine white Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, divested of all those A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cides, and acrimonious Particles of the Salt and Vitriol which had caused its Sublimation. This Mercury thus prepared, is proper to purge withal, joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to some other Cathartick, in the beginning of Continual, Putrid and Malignant Fevers; because that more than all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers it penetrates, it resists the putrefaction, casts forth the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trid
<pb facs="tcp:59497:21"/>Matter; and that it neither acts on the parts, it does not heat, nor augment the Ardor of the Fever; but on the other hand, it is a most powerful Dulcifier of all Acides, and therefore proper likewise in the Cure of Fevers.</p>
            <p>To preserve your Menstru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, which has been used in the preparation of the Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, distill it very gently, and in the Bottom of the Vessel, there will remain that portion of Acides that the Mercury was impregnated withal, and the Essential Salt sublimed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove it. The same Menstruum will serve to prepare the Lead with, as follows.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:59497:21"/>
            <p>Take as much as you please of <hi>Saccharum Saturni;</hi> pour o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it of the diluted volatil Salt of Tartar, as was used for the Mercury; set it to digest and circulate, as you did the Mercury; and thus it will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posite that Acidity, which had been joyned to it in its Redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction into Salt from Lead. This is also, a very great Extinguish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Internal Inflammations, and a Strengthner of the <hi>Vis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cera.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As to what concerns Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, its Calcination with Tartar, in lieu of Nitre, and Dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cisication, making it a perfect Alkaly; it needs no farther preparation, but may, with ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good Success, be admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stred
<pb facs="tcp:59497:22"/>also in Fevers, as an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Diaphoretick and Diu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick.</p>
            <p>This Mineral abounds in a Noble Mineral Sulphur; it partakes also, of a Metallick Indigested Mercury, and of a small proportion of Salt. It is of an <hi>Hermaphrodite</hi> Nature, fix'd and volatil, of a Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rament Hot, Cold, Dry and Moist; out of it may be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted particular Medicines for each Disease; besides, an Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versal <hi>Panacea.</hi> It is a great Purifier of the Blood, and Dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifier of Acides.</p>
            <p>Sal Armoniac, is to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared in this manner, for to be administred in Fevers.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:59497:22"/>
            <p>Take of Sal Armoniac, and of Salt of Tartar, of each about half a pound, mix them in Powder well together, and put them into a Glass cucurbit, sprinkling of it with four or five spoonfuls of Spring Water; fit a Head and Receiver, both well luted; distill in Sand with a gentle Fire, that the Spirits may come over leisurely: when there distills no more, remove the Receiver; then increase the Fire to the third degree, and continue it for two hours, and there will sublime the Flowers of the Sal Armoniac.</p>
            <p>There will remain at the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of the Body, the white Febrifuge Salt, in a white Mass, dissolve it in Common Water,
<pb facs="tcp:59497:23"/>filtre, and evaporate to Dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness. This Salt works by U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine, and but rarely by Sweats; by which means, it opens Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions, and expells Acides.</p>
            <p>Now I come to the prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Vipers: It is a Serpent, the most Venemous of all Rep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tils, apt to be irritated. This long lived Animal, doth not only renew those that make fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Use of its Preparation, but renews it self also. Its Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues are to resist all Poysons, malignant and putrid Humors; driving forth all the Serosities which infect the Mass of Blood; dulcifies Acides, strengthens all the Noble parts, and quickens, and enlivens the Spirits, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they are enabled to expell
<pb facs="tcp:59497:23"/>the Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sick Leven of Fevers. Its preparation is a follows.</p>
            <p>Take Vipers, put them into a close Matrass, pour over them of strong Spirit of Wine, accua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Essential Salt of Tartar above-mentioned, as much as will serve to suffocate them. Fit a Head into this Matrass, set it <hi>in Balneo;</hi> add a Receiver, lute all well; and there let it stand till the Vipers are dead: After a due Digesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, draw off half the quantity of the Menstruum; pour off the other half by Decantation; then pour over them the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining part of the Distilled Spirit, which was first distilled, and after Digestion, distill half of it off again, and the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:59497:24"/>part; pour off as before, which must be very hard press'd from the Vipers, and joyned with the first impregnated Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struum; then filtrate, and keep them close stopped in a Glass.</p>
            <p>Take the Vipers very well dried, so that they may be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily crumbled into Powder with the Hands; set them in a Glass Retort, to which, fit and lute a large Receiver; distill them in an open Fire, observing the Degrees of Heat, till all that is in the Retort, be dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven over by the violence of a flaming Fire: The Distillation being ended, the Volatil Salt will be found partly dissolved in the Water contained in the Receiver; and partly adherent
<pb facs="tcp:59497:24"/>unto the sides of the Receiver, which is to be washed off with the said Water; then separate it from its Foetid Oyl, through a Filtre of Paper. This Vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til Salt, is afterwards to be parted from the foetid bitter Water, by a gentle Sublimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in a long Neck'd Glass, with its Head and Receiver, so that the Humidity mount not with the Salt.</p>
            <p>Joyn this Volatil Salt to the fore-mentioned Essence of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, which, set to digest in a Glass well stopped, during two or three days; and so you will have the preparation of Vipers.</p>
            <p>Now there remains nothing but the Preparation of Gold,
<pb facs="tcp:59497:25"/>and of its Dissolvent, and the preparation of the <hi>Quinquina;</hi> but the Author of this Discourse upon the <hi>Quinquina,</hi> having al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, both sufficiently and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciously treated on that point; I shall only add, that an Extract may be made of it, through the Use of Spirit of Wine, impreg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated with the Essential Salt of Tartar, without any Acidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which may be a more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Menstruum and Vehicle to extract the Tincture, and to administer it in, than any other that I know of: And now I shall come to the preparation of Gold, and of its Dissolvent.</p>
            <p>Gold is the most perfect of Mettals; the <hi>Ne plus ultra</hi> of the Mineral Power; It is a most
<pb facs="tcp:59497:25"/>compact and solid Mettal, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded of fix'd and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent Principles, digested in a most high degree, as its In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corruptability does manifest. Its Fixidity, purity, and its most Cordial Vertues, make it to be dedicated unto the Heart in particular, but it is not only a Sovereign Cordial, it is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Purifier of the Blood also, from all Acides, and super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous Serosities, dulcifying, dispersing, and driving forth by Transpirations, all Heterogeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and corrupted Humors of the Body, which are the Results of the divers Alterations of the Blood, tending to Corruption and Putrefaction, whence are produced divers sorts of Fevers.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:59497:26"/>
            <p>But Gold in its Natural com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pactness, cannot operate to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Advantage in Physick; it must first be opened, and the more it is radically opened, the greater Effects it must con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently produce: Therefore I have made Choice of such a Menstruum, as through its Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy and great Affinity with that Mettal, does so prepare and dissolve it, that though it may be reduced again in part, yet not without a sensible de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay of its weight, after every Dissolution and Reduction.</p>
            <p>A Particular property may be attributed to this Dissol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, which is, that though it so powerfully acts upon Gold, dissolving it without any Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal
<pb facs="tcp:59497:26"/>Heat, inward Corrosion, or the least Sign of any Effer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vescency, but just like a Salt in Water, yet it will not so much as touch any other Mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of either of Nature's Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies; which proves its Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon Gold, to proceed from an Analogical Harmony of Parts, and through meer Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy; but after the Dissolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the unprepared Gold in this Dissolvent, from a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanous, pleasant, Acide-Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor that it was, it becomes of a most glorious Golden Color, of an austere Taste and Smell, and tinges most things of a curious Purple Color, which clearly demonstrates, that the Menstruum is sufficiently sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turated, with the Central
<pb facs="tcp:59497:27"/>Sulphur of the Gold, which yields that pleasant Color.</p>
            <p>Gold thus prepared, and the Menstruum drawn off by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stillation, does yield its Tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, in almost any Liquor; but more chiefly in a Spirit of Wine, accuated as before, with the Essential Salt of Tartar: which Tincture does variously operate, sometimes purging, sometimes (though rarely) vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miting, frequently by Urines, and most commonly by Sweats: By all which ways, its Vertues are sensibly felt, in augmenting the Strength, refreshing the Spirits, cherishing the Heart, and corroborating of all the <hi>Viscera.</hi> The preparation of this Dissolvent is as follows:</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:59497:27"/>
            <p>Take of Salt Gemme what you please, make it into Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; put it in a Crucible, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a naked Fire during six or seven hours; then take the Crucible from the Fire, let it cool, break it, take the Calci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned matter, and make it into fine Powder; then put it into a Glass Retort, pour over it half its weight of Oyl of Vitri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ol; joyn the Retort to a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiver, with a little Water in it, to condense the Fumes, and lute them well; then increasing the Fire by Degrees, distill to a perfect Driness; in which you will find, that the Oyl of Vitriol will remain all behind, with the fix'd parts of the Salt Gemme; and that only the Spirit of the Salt Gemme, will
<pb facs="tcp:59497:28"/>come over in Fumes; break the Retort, take out the Matter, make it into Powder, and put it into an Earthen Retort, with a fit Receiver, well luted; give it a strong Flame Fire, till that all the Residue of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Salt Gemme be come o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; Rectifie this Spirit divers times, and keep it for use.</p>
            <p>Then take of <hi>Regulus Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sophorum,</hi> made of <hi>Antimony, Mars, Venus</hi> and <hi>Saturn,</hi> two parts, of Sulphur one part; melt them together in a Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, after they have been made into Powder, and mixed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, separate the purified <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulus</hi> from the Scurf; take of this refined <hi>Regulus</hi> in Powder, and of Nitre equal parts, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine
<pb facs="tcp:59497:28"/>it in an Earthen Pan, over a Fire, continually stirring, till the Nitre has ended its Fulmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; then take that Matter, and make it into Powder a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; put it in a Crucible, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it, and set it in a Fire, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring four Hours, glowing hot, but so as it does not melt; take it out of the Crucible, the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter will be of a greenish Color; make it again into Powder, put it in a Glass Retort, pour o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it the Spirit of Salt Gemme, lute a Receiver to it, let it stand in Digestion, in Sand, during half a Day; then di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>still gradually to perfect Dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness; observe to put some Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the Receiver, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dense the Fumes; rectifie the Distilled Liquor six or seven
<pb facs="tcp:59497:29"/>times; and then you have the Dissolvent, which is potable, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven before that the Gold is dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved in it.</p>
            <p>Take of this Dissolvent, which is call'd by some Authors, <hi>Mercurius Philosophorum,</hi> nine parts, of laminated Gold, cemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with Antimony, to deprive it of all Impurities, one part; mix them, and leave them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in a Matrass without heat, and in 24 hours the Gold will be dissolv'd; close the Glass Hermetically (or adding a blind Head to it) set it to circulate in a gentle lamp heat, during forty days; then having poured the Liquor into a little Glass Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tort, draw off the Menstruum, till the Saffron of the Gold re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main
<pb facs="tcp:59497:29"/>almost dry; pour upon it of the accuated Spirit of Wine, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>o the height of three Fingers <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>readth; stop and lute the Glass very well, set it in Digestion <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>uring 10 or 12 days; and it will be totally impregnated, and <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>he Crocus of Gold totally dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>olved.</p>
            <p>Thus I have given you the Preparations of such Remedies as I have found by my own Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience to be every one by <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>hemselves very powerful in the Cure of Fevers and Agues; but most efficacious, when join<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together with the <hi>Quinquina:</hi> for then there are no sorts of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cides, or evil Ferments, but that are overcome by that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded Extract, after due Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation,
<pb facs="tcp:59497:30"/>with the above-menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned Mercury, added unto some other proper Purgatives: And from the use of this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract may likewise be expected a powerful Vertue in preserva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Renovation of Health. The proportions of the Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations in the making up of this compounded Febrifuge and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newer, are as follows:</p>
            <p>Take of the Extract of the <hi>Peruvian</hi> Bark, made with the accuated Spirit of Wine, three ounces, of the extract of Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taury made with the same Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struum, one ounce, of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract of <hi>Opium,</hi> prepared after the same manner, one Dram, of the tincture of Coral one ounce, of prepar'd Allum-six drams, of the
<pb facs="tcp:59497:30"/>
               <hi>Saccharum Satuani</hi> two drams, of the Diaphoretick of Antimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ten drams, of the Sal Armo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niack eight drams, of the Es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence of Vipers ten drams, of the Tincture of Gold one ounce.</p>
            <p>Put all these Preparations well mixed together, in a Glass Matrass, and pour over them as much of the accuated Spirit of Wine as will cover them three Fingers breadth; set them to dissolve, digest and circulate <hi>in Balneo,</hi> during 10 days; then draw off the Spirit to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistency of Hony.</p>
            <p>Of this Extract, give for a common Dose, to the quantity of half an ounce, which must be repeated between every Fit
<pb facs="tcp:59497:31"/>of an Ague, two or three times, according as the Violence of the Fever, and the strength of the Patient, will indicate the Able Physitian to act. I fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther refer the Reader unto the Method which our Author has laid down for an Example, which being the same as I use in the Administration of this Extract: It will therefore save me the labour of saying any more; but that this Extract is to be given of it self, in a Spoon, or on the point of a Knife, or diluted in any kind of Febri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge Waters, according to the Patient's pleasure.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59497:31"/>
            <head>OF THE CURE OF FEVERS, Performed by the QUIN QUINA, OR <hi>Jesuits Powder.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHat Cure soever we bring in order to new Discoveries, or in accomplishing those which others have first light up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we cannot but let pass an
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:59497:32"/>infinity of things; and we can never throughly behold all those things which Nature does in a manner expose before our Eyes. We have a President of this in the <hi>Quinquina, Peruvian</hi>-Bark, or <hi>Jesuits Powder,</hi> take which term you please, seeing that amongst divers other Denominations, these are those under which that Febrifuge we treat of at present is most generally known, which, without Contradiction, is the most certain Remedy for the Cure of Fevers or Agues as has hitherto been discover'd. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, whether it is through a prepossession against Novelties, or a distrust of unknown Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies; or whether it be through such unto which the Sick were formerly Subject; it has been,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:59497:32"/>for a considerable time, in a manner abandoned, though it deserv'd a better Fate.</p>
            <p>About thirty years since, this Remedy came into <hi>Europe:</hi> It is the Bark of a Tree which grows at <hi>Perue,</hi> by the <hi>Indians</hi> named <hi>Kina,</hi> and by the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards, Palo de Calenturas,</hi> the Wood of Fevers. These last di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide it into two sorts, of which, the one is cultivated, and of a better Nature, the other is sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vage, and much inferiour in Vertue.</p>
            <p>Some Authors did at that time give both the Description, and Figure of that Tree, and they did likewise mention something con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the qualities of its Bark; from that very time also it was observ'd by some Experiments
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59497:33"/>which were made on <hi>Quartain</hi> Agues, and afterwards on inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittent Fevers, that in giving the <hi>Quinquina</hi> in Substance with Wine once or twice at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the Access, it frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly did cure those sorts of Fevers, though they were apt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn.</p>
            <p>A Physitian at <hi>Bruxells,</hi> did near-upon that time write against the use of that Remedy; but his reasons were not so positive as to remain without Answer. A certain <hi>Anonymous</hi> Author did put forth one; and some few years after, a Learned Physitian of <hi>Lovain,</hi> published a Book on that Subject, in which, he treats of the Vertues and Properties of the <hi>Quinquina,</hi> so far as his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments, which were but few,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:59497:33"/>had given him Light therein. He powerfully answers to those Objections which were then al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leag'd against its Use; and also lays down good Preparations of it.</p>
            <p>Since then, and during near twenty years, the <hi>Quinquina</hi> has had its Approvers, as well as its Enemies, according as each have made a good, or a bad Use of it, without any Alteration in its Preparation, or in the manner of its Administration.</p>
            <p>But of late Years, there has been a greater Endeavour used towards its setting forth. Some have caused it to be taken in a solid Form: Others have thought it more fit to give it in Liquor: Some applying themselves more to the time, than to the manner
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59497:34"/>of exhibiting it, in lieu of causing it to be taken as formerly; at the beginning of the access, they have preferr'd the space of the intermission; and finally it has been given in divers Doses, and during some time, more or less.</p>
            <p>An able Physitian of <hi>London,</hi> in a Treatise which he has set forth of acute Diseases, alleadges very powerful reasons as to this Method. He prefers it to all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in his practice, though with a little too much of Caution: for having not put forward his Experiments to that height, that they might be improved: Others finally have made a Secret of this Remedy; and at the same time, they have not omitted that way of giving it, which they
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59497:34"/>have done with very little Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumspection, and much of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence; and peradventure, that that same Confidence has not been useless as to the upholding of their Reputation.</p>
            <p>This is what hitherto has been the Destiny of the <hi>Quinquina:</hi> Mean time it is most certain, that if from the first Experiments we had further extended our Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions than we have done, a greater advantage had been reap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from those first Essays, whence to have drawn in the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, all those advantages which might reasonably be expected.</p>
            <p>The first Reflection which was to be done, was on the manner of giving the <hi>Quinquina:</hi> For it is something strange, that during so long a time, persons have been
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59497:35"/>satisfied with the giving of two Drams of Powder, diluted in a little Proportion of Wine, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out considering that it might be too great a Proportion for one single Dose, and likewise too little for a perfect Cure.</p>
            <p>The second, and most power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Reflection, ought to have been on the time in which this Remedy is to be used. It was a thing of Consequence, to examine at what time it were most advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageously to be taken, in or out of the Fit; and whether it was to be repeated and given at se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral times, to cure more certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and to prevent Relapses.</p>
            <p>Finally, some Reflections ought to have been made on so sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing a manner of Cure to find out the Reasons, and from
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59497:35"/>thence have drawn solid Conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences, that the Action and Vertue of that Remedy might not be lock'd up within those narrow Limits as was at that time prescribed in it.</p>
            <p>My Design therefore, is to make known the Preparations of the <hi>Quinquina,</hi> to expound, as much as in me lies, its Vertues and Action, to set forth the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of using it in all Fevers indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently; and lastly, to answer unto all those Objections that may be offer'd against it.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Preparations of the Remedy.</head>
               <p>BEfore I give the Preparation of this Remedy, it is to be observ'd, in the first place, that the <hi>Quinquina</hi> can be prepar'd
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59497:36"/>after-divers manners without any Detriment to its Vertue. I there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore pretend not to offer such a Preparation as will exclude all others; every one may stick to that Method of which he has had best Experience and Success: for I give not mine for Rules, but for Examples only.</p>
               <p>The second thing that is to be observed (that we may not easi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly give Faith unto those that make Mysteries of their Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies) is, that in what manner soever the <hi>Quinquina</hi> is given, it is always the principal Ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, not to say the only, unto which is due the Cure of Fevers; and that all that can be added unto it, can at the best but serve to assist it in the Action.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:59497:36"/>
               <p>The third Observation which is to be made, is not to add any thing unto the <hi>Quinquina</hi> which may hinder, or retard its action. To that purpose, its qualities are to be exactly known, that nothing be added which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary unto them. Those Disgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses which those persons might add unto it, that for their own profit would make a Secret of it, not having peradventure a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Knowledge of the said Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, no more than of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject on which it ought to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied: Those Disguises, I say, might be extreamly prejudicial to the Sick; and even hinder, or at least retard their Cure; that this Advice is necessarily given, to prevent that Abuse, let those be Judge that act knowingly,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59497:37"/>and with a good Conscience.</p>
               <p>Lastly, The Fourth thing to be observed, has a Respect to the certainty of the Cure. To this purpose it is to be noted, That after what manner soever the <hi>Quinquina</hi> is prepared, such a certain Quantity ought to be taken of it, as may perfectly cure, and without Return; though that this cannot be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cisely determinated indifferently in all sorts of Fevers, and Habits of Bodies: Yet in order to some kind of Rule in general, it suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices to say, that of what Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration soever, there must com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly be emplyed for the Cure of each person, an ounce and half, or two ounces of the <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quina;</hi> and that that quantity also may be augmented accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:59497:37"/>to the divers occasions. There will be some Persons found, doubtless, that will be so happy as to be cured with a far less proportion than I have said, es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in a favourable Season; and when that the Fever is in its beginning, or but moderate: But as I have no other Design, than to propose that Proportion which is best and most certain; I therefore extend the Dose un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that quantity: For Reason and Experience shewing, that there is no hazard in the Use of this Remedy; it is always bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to take more than less of it, thereby to be the more certain of a perfect Cure. I come now to its Preparation.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Quinquina</hi> may be given in a solid form, or in Liquor;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:59497:38"/>solid, as in a Bolus, or an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract.</p>
               <p>To give it in a Bolus, it must be made into a very fine Powder, and mixed with some Extract, as that of Juniper-Berries, or with some Syrup or Conserve, as that of Clove-Gilly flower or of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigold. To give it in Extract, the Tincture is to be drawn out with <hi>Aqua vitae,</hi> or with Simple, or Compounded Spirit of Wine, and then reduced to the Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stency of Honey. This Prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, more than all others, requires a good Artist.</p>
               <p>If one would give it in Liquor, it must either be in Tincture, or in Infusion. In Tincture, as that of which the Extract is made more weak or more strong, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to pleasure, or as one
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59497:38"/>would give it in greater or lesser quantity; so more or less of the Spirit of Wine must be drawn off again by Distillation: Which Tincture may be afterwards given in any convenient Liquor.</p>
               <p>If it be given in Infusion, it must be made with Wine, or with some other Liquor, without heat, or with heat, either in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusing of the <hi>Quinquina</hi> by it self, or with Addition of other things. Hereafter follows a Preparation made with Wine.</p>
               <p>There must be had four quarts of White Wine, or Claret Wine, that of the two, that has less of green, and more of delicateness than of strength in it, put into it an ounce and an half, or two ounces of <hi>Quinquina,</hi> made into fine Powder; half an handful of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:59497:39"/>the Flowers of little Centaury; two drams of the Salt of the same Plant, and as much of good white Tartar; or in lieu of those two Salts, two drams of Sal-Armoniac very well purified; one dram or two of Sassafrax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, cut in small pieces; or one dram of Juniper-Berries, or of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Aromaticks, more to please the Palate of the Sick, than to add to the Cure. The Salts might be left out also in augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the dose of the <hi>Quinquina.</hi> Let all be infus'd by the space of twenty four hours on warm Embers, in a well clos'd Vessel; after which, the Infusion shall be strained or filtrated for use.</p>
               <p>But there is nothing less un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful, and more easie than the following Preparations.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:59497:39"/>
               <p>Let there be put into an Hogs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head of Wine, of <hi>Quinquina</hi> made into Powder, the quantity of three drams, or half an ounce to every quart, or more, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the strength that would be given unto the Liquor: Add of Sassafrax-wood, of Little-Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, of the Juniper-berries, and of Sal Armoniack, of all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable to the quart of Wine contained in the Vessel, observ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the same Doses as were given in the foregoing Infusion: Let the Vessel be rowl'd up and down divers times, during divers days; to make an exact mixture, and to excite a Fermentation, which, though but small, will not be use<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less: After which, leave it to set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and to clear.</p>
               <p>This very Preparation will be
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:59497:40"/>better yet, and more pleasant, if it is performed in Vintage time, mixing of those things with the Wine when it is working; and that nothing of the Vertue of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> may be lost, let the <hi>Quinquina,</hi> and the other Ingredients be fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented at first with the Wine in the same Vessel in which it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign'd to be kept; and let not the Vessel be fill'd up, nor stop it over close, least that during the Fermentation, part of the Wine and Remedy work over; let all be frequently stirr'd, or let the Vessel be rowl'd from time to time so long as the Wine is in Fermentation; and when that the heat is over, the Vessel must be filled up with more of the same Wine; and being well stopt, let all rest to clear perfectly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is used.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:59497:40"/>
               <p>Those that understand the Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of Fermentation, will know the usefulness of it here, which will serve to loosen the most subtle and most active parts, from the gros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sest and most material, both of the Wine, and of the Remedy; by which means its Action and Vertue will be the more power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, without the Addition of Salts, as in the other Preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; nor of any other Agents, than those which are in the Wine, which at the same time cause the Fermentation of the Wine, and of the Remedy; and will serve to augment its Activity and Pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tration.</p>
               <p>A Beer or Ale may likewise be prepared with the same Remedy, in favour to those that are accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stomed to that sort of Liquor:
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:59497:41"/>It will acquire the same Vertue<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> that the Wine has; provided, that the Dose of the <hi>Quinquin<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> be augmented the third part, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thereunto Juniper, Worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, or some other thing that will give the Drink a grateful Taste, and prevent it from sowr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>If you would have the Infusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on made with some other Liquor, the following Preparation will serve for an Example, in such oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions as will be judged necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to prefer it to another.</p>
               <p>Take 2 quarts of those Waters which are commonly used in Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, as that of Fennel, Parsley, of Little Centaury, or of such like. Let every quart be accua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with a Spoonful of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Wine, or with as much of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:59497:41"/>the Tincture of the <hi>Quinquina:</hi> Let there be put into those Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters an ounce and half of <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quina</hi> in Powder, two Pugils of the Flowers of small Centaury, three drams of its Salt; set all in a Sand Bath, in a small Glass Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, covered and close luted with another, the Mouth downwards: Let it infuse with a gentle Heat 24 hours, or during the necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry time required to draw forth its Tincture.</p>
               <p>Its Infusion may be made like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise with Common Ptisanes, as with Common Water also; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, that the quantity of the <hi>Quinquina</hi> be augmented, with some addition of apperitive Salts, or of something else, which will help the Liquor to be well im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnated with the Tincture:
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:59497:42"/>Let the Vessel be close stopp'd, and allow a longer time to the Iufusion, it being not wholly ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary to use Wine in the draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Tincture of the <hi>Quinqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> or other spirituous things.</p>
               <p>These are the Preparations which I have most happily made use of; mean time I prefer in many occasions the Infusion made with Wine, and above all, that made in Vintage time: For those reasons which I shall alledge in treating of the Use of this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy; therefore that Preparation before all others, shall serve me for Example; in which, for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, I will not advance any thing but what shall be grounded on a great number of Experiences.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:59497:42"/>
               <head>Of the Action of the Remedy.</head>
               <p>IT is not to be expected, that I should set forth throughly, and without any doubt, the whole manner after which the <hi>Quinqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> does act; seeing that Nature has conceal'd it from us, as she has done divers other of her Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions: I shall be contented in only giving my Conjectures as far as in me lies: To that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose it is requisite to lay down a general <hi>Idea</hi> of the Subject on which it acts.</p>
               <p>It is to be imagin'd then, that a Fever or Ague is an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Boyling or Fermentation, excited in the Mass of Blood; that this Fermentation against Nature does alter the Blood, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sturbs
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:59497:43"/>its motion, and perverts the Oeconomy of the whole Body, that the principle or immediate Cause of that Fermentation, is an evil Leven, which partakes of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cides or Sharpness, which infects and agitates the Humours in divers manners, whence proceeds the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of Fevers, as well as the Division which may be made of them, into intermittent, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual, accidental or Symptoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Fevers.</p>
               <p>In the intermittent Fevers, this Leven does often arise from a portion of bad Chyle, or from those Aliments which we have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, of which the first Degree of Corruption, is to contract a fermentative Eagerness, which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cites the Fever. Those strange Juices not being capable of joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:59497:43"/>with the rest of the Mass of Blood, cause in it a boyling and <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> disturbance, till they be corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, or seperated from the other Humours.</p>
               <p>In Continual Fevers, the same Ferment is ingendred from the same Aliment, or from the whole Mass of Blood; which Ferment, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s it circulates with the Blood, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ugments its Sharpness, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces that violent effervency which causes the Continuation and Height of the Fever, which produces a disorder and disunion <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>n all the parts of the Blood, in which the most spirituous Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>les are loosened from the gros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>est, and set into a Motion, and <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>n a Degree of Exaltation, whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>y contrary to Nature, which <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ever ceases, till those impetuous
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:59497:44"/>Spirits are perfectly calmed or dissipated in some manner or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>Finally, in the Accidental Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, under which are to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended the Languide Fevers, or those that proceed from Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions, those that happen by defluxions, or by the fall of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours on some part; the malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Fevers which comprehend the <hi>Measels, Small Pox,</hi> the <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, &amp;c.</hi> In all those Fevers, I say, which chiefly proceed from too great a Coagulation of some parts of the Blood, and of a too great fluidity of the others, as i<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> might be shewn in those parts, that some Ferment is the Cause thereof, in separating the most subtile and most thin parts of the blood from the grossest and most
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:59497:44"/>thick. Those Particulars thus disunited by the eagerness or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidity of that Ferment do Justle and oppose one another; some congeale and coagulate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, and lie corrupting in some parts of the Body, while that the others set themselves in a more fierce agitation, and rowl with a more rapid motion in the Ves<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sels: Thus the Natural Circula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the equal motion of the Blood is interruped and disturb'd, which interruption never ceases, but by the Re-union, and the Calm of all those parts, or by the dissipation of that which cannot change its Nature; and above all, by the destruction of that Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that is the Cause of all that Disorder.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:59497:45"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:59497:45"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:59497:46"/>
               <p>What I have now said of this ferment or acide Leven as the principal Cause of all Fevers might be further proved by the Effects, that is, by all the accidents which happen to Fevers: It is doubtless that Leven which at the beginning of Intermittent Fevers, causes the cold and shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verings, the weariness and pains and the difficulties of Respiration, in retarding the Circulation of the Blood by the constriction of its parts and Vessels, which is the Property of the acide or eager so to do: The Ardor, the excess of Drought, the Head-Aches, the restlessness, the convulsive moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons proceed also from a strong Acrimony, and from a most vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Action of that Leven upon the Humors, which causes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:59497:46"/>a more strong effervescency, and a more hasty Circulation, which does last till that the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is gone through the Pores by Sweats, or is exhalated through Transpiration. Thus the Fever ceases, because that the Cause thereof is dissipated.</p>
               <p>It is by that reason also, that those Sweats which smell eager, or that are accompanied with redness and heats in the Skin, are more critical than others; and mark that those eagers and acides are so entirely carried off by that means, as not to produce new Fermentations. Those lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Blisters also which appear a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Lips and other parts of the Face, are indications of the coming forth of that Leven, and though they appear never so small;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:59497:47"/>they are not less, the undoubted marks of the discharge which has been made of that Leven by the whole habit of the Body.</p>
               <p>If that these Observations would not lead us too far, we should make it appear, that any of those Effects could not be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to any other Cause than that which we have mentioned; at least it cannot be gain-said, but that this Leven has the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Share in it, and that it predo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minates over the other Causes through the vigour of its Action, if not by its quantity. I will not except Choler, which is almost al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways accus'd of all the accidents of Fevers, while that it often pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vails over the other Humors without producing any Motion of Fevers, as it may be observ'd
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:59497:47"/>in divers Diseases; as for Example, in the Jaundies, in which Choler communicates its Tincture in an high Degree unto the Blood, and unto all the parts of the Body, without having of a Fever always annexed unto it, or at least any that is considerable. This might persuade, by the by, that this Choler is less the Cause than the Effect of the Fermentation of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, or at least that Choler can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not produce a Fever without a mixture of such a Ferment as I have now mentioned.</p>
               <p>To know yet more precisely whether this Leven predominates effectively at the time of the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, it were not amiss, in imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of a <hi>Danish</hi> Physitian, who is very Learned and Curious, to distil the Blood of some Fever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ish
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:59497:48"/>Person: He has observ'd in that Distillation, that there is less of Volatil Salt than in the Blood of sound Bodies, whence might be inferr'd, that acide and eager Particles do predominate over the Violatil and Spirituous parts, as it happens to Wines that turn to Vinegars, which happens both in the Wine and the Blood, through a Dissipation of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits and an Augmentation or Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplication of their acide parts, which manner is easie to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by those that understand Chymistry.</p>
               <p>Having suppos'd what I have newly said, that it is an acide Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven which is the cause of Fevers, as well as of their Accidents; if on the other hand an Examen be made, either by Fire, or by any
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:59497:48"/>other ways that may give to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand the Nature of this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy then what is truth will be discovered, namely, that it is compos'd of subtil pricking and bitter parts, which are joyned unto some roughness or harshness somewhat Astringent: Its Bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness does combate and mortifies the Leven of Fevers, for bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and acidity are incompatible, it being proper to both to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy one another, as it might be prov'd by divers reasonings, and many Experiments, which would lead us too far; the subtilty of its parts, and their Penetrations, serve to resolve, and to dissipate that Leven, and to hinder, or to destroy the Coagulation of the Humors; its Harshness and Astriction does calm and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:59497:49"/>their Ebulitions and Agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, at the same time strength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ening those parts in which that Leven had made some Impressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>It is on those Principles that it may be said, that in all Fevers indifferently, this Remedy can combate, mortifie and resolve that bad Leven; that it alters and changes it, or that it helps Nature to drive it out of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy by some sensible or insensible ways, that its Action extends e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to continual Fevers, as well as to the Intermittent; that Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven being as I have said, almost of the same Nature in the one as in the others, not differing but by some degrees of Fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and Activity; so that the divers Fire-Hearths in which the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:59497:49"/>Fevers are pretended to be kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, or the different Seats which they seem to possess, hinder not, but that the Remedy carries its Vertue every where, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes that Leven how difficult soever it be to be destroyed.</p>
               <p>This is, in few Words, what is the Vertue of this Remedy; and though that the <hi>Quinquina</hi> be the Principal Subject, the same thing may be said of the little Centaury in some measure also: It is bitter and apperitive, detersive, and lightly astringent, so that posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing such qualities as are near un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to those of the <hi>Quinquina,</hi> it may be allow'd, at least to assist in its Operation. Of Truth, Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence has learned us, that when those two Remedies are conjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together, there is yet a greater
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:59497:50"/>Certainty of the Cure. It has al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so been seen divers times, that the bare Decoction of the little Centaury does cure Fevers that are somewhat stubborn: The Salts are added unto it to convey in all places the Faculty of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, as well as their own appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritive and detersive Vertue, and to draw along with them the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Leven. The rest is added but to give Vigor unto the Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, which is commonly the Seat of the most troublesome Accidents of Fevers.</p>
               <p>Besides all that hath been men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, there may be further ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to this Remedy a Tincture of <hi>Laudanum,</hi> when that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns or the Accesses are violent; and that the great Fermentation, which is the cause of it, is sudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:59497:50"/>to be suppressed, as well as the impetuous Agitation of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits: Its Bitterness and Harshness which have some Affinity with that of the <hi>Quinquina;</hi> and may also serve to oppose the Leven of the Fevers, as well as the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty which it has of procuring Sweats or Transpiration, can cause an exhalation of the matter of this Leven: It is fruitless to object, that it hinders other Evacuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: It does not so, when that it is given at several times, and in small quantities; and in case it should, it would be but for some Moments; whereas the calm that it produces to the Humors, and the Transpiration that it cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, are far more salubrious than the Suspention of some other E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacuations is hurtful. If I would
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:59497:51"/>back this Practice with Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, I should make use of those of the greatest Physicians in An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, who have made use of <hi>Opium</hi> and other Narcoticks in the Cure of divers Fevers, as well as divers able Practitioners in these days make use of the <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danum</hi> on the same account; but as it is not absolutely neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary to conjoyn it to the <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quina,</hi> and that it is a Remedy which ought to be used with great Circumspection, I refer it unto the Prudence and Ability of the Physician. I shall only say in general, that if at any time it is thought fit to be added, it must be in a very small Dose, as of a quarter or half a Grain for a Dose: and as to the number of Doses in which it ought to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:59497:51"/>enter, and the time in which it ought to be used; there are none but the Physicians that can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe it.</p>
               <p>Further, to confirm all that I have said concerning the opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and power of this Remedy, it is to be observed, according as experience has divers times taught me, that it has this further in particular, it commonly takes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the most part of those Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents that accompany Fevers, as are the Swellings, and the pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Extensions of the Belly, the Obstructions of the Liver, Spleen, and other parts, the loss of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite, Indigestions, Flux of the Belly, and other Disorders which are most commonly found to be dissipated, at the same time as the Cure of the Fever is perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med;
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:59497:52"/>which will not be difficult to conceive after some Reflections made on the Qualities of this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, seeing that through its Bitterness, Austerity and Astri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, it ought to strengthen and restringe all the Fibres of the parts, and give them Vigor suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to reject all that is of a strange Nature, at the same time that through its detersive and apperitive Faculty, it carries off the causes of Obstructions through the divers ways which Nature has appointed.</p>
               <p>These are my Conjectures on the Vertues and Operations of the <hi>Quinquina:</hi> If it is objected, that there are other Remedies in Nature, which apparently pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sess the same Qualities, and that yet produce not the same effects:
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:59497:52"/>I will ingenuously answer, That there is something particular in the Union of the Qualities of this Remedy, or in the Contex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of its parts, which gives it a more singular Power, than to all other Remedies of destroying the Fermentation of Fevers; that this Union or Contexture, is wholly unknown to use; and that we do not understand, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in what precisely consists that Fermentation which it ought to extinguish. From thence may be concluded, that this Remedy acts on this Fermentation, through such Engines as are concealed from us, and that will for ever be the Subject of our Admiration.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:59497:53"/>
               <head>The Ʋse of the Remedy.</head>
               <p>SOme Observations are to be made on those things which are to be put in Practice, before, as well as after, the Use of the Remedy.</p>
               <p>The first Observation has a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect to Bleeding; of truth, in divers occasions its use cannot be dispenc'd with before the taking of the Remedy; yet Care must be had least that the abuse of it should drain the Strength, and alter all the Blood, and the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the parts, which would be capable of hindering, or of retarding the Action of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, which in this Disorder, could not make a sufficient Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression of its Vertue: For it is
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:59497:53"/>certain, that some Persons that have been weakened through Bleeding, and the use of other Remedies, as well as through the length of the Disease, have had occasion to use longer than ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily this Remedy before they could be perfectly recovered. In such an occasion, therefore the Patient ought to be directed and guided by an able Physician, that knows how to make a fit use of Bleeding, to ease the Vessels when they are too full, and to diminish the too great Ebuslition of the Blood: After which, for certain, the Remedy will be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministred with a more suddain, and more happy Success.</p>
               <p>The Second thing to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serv'd, is the Purgation; it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry useful before the taking of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:59497:54"/>the <hi>Quinquina,</hi> when that there are many Impurities lodg'd in the lower Belly; and that the first Passages are not free: They are so many Obstacles unto the Operation of the Remedy, which ought not to meet any thing that would stop it in its way, or would mix with it: mean time it is to be observed also, that it is not necessary, in order to the giving of it, to drain all the ill Humors, because, that frequently in the discharging of them, the Leven of the Fever is augmented, which at each access or return, may strengthen it self, and make a further Progress, what Evacuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on soever is made of the said Humours, which in success of time, become more the Effect than the Cause of the Fever:
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:59497:54"/>Besides, after that through the Use of the Remedy the Fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, and consequently the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is made to cease; those Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatives being then given, will ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily carry off all that matter which did entertain that Fermentation and Fever.</p>
               <p>The Third Observation con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns Diet; for though that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out observing of any, a Cure may be had, by the use of the Remedy, it is a great Error to despise the Rules of Diet at such a time as that the Fever weakens the parts, and disturbs their Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. It is not to be expected therefore, that through the Use of the <hi>Quinquina,</hi> a Body may be raised above all those Disorders that an ill Diet might cause, and beyond those evil Consequences
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:59497:55"/>that might happen thereon. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides, the Blood being infected with those evil Juices that the bad Diet would have introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, it would not then be so fit to receive the Impression of the <hi>Quinquina,</hi> which requires as much as can be, a Blood full of Spirits, and disingag'd of all its Impurities; but yet the goodness and Vertue of this Remedy does sometimes allow of some small Trespasses beyond the Rules of Physick: And it is to be observ'd, that there are divers Fevers in which a solid Food and Wine al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so, is to be prefer'd unto such A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liments as are more refreshing and moist, because that the first have a greater Affinity with the Remedy, and may aid it in some manner to dissipate the Leven of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:59497:55"/>Fevers, in lieu that the others might retard its Action, and the Impression of its Vertue: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all that is apt to be ill dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted and distributed, is to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided, as also all that is eager, or that will turn eager, or be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sily corrupted, as all sorts of Milk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meats, Sauces, Pulces, Fruits, and the like; and generally all that would augment the matter of this Ferment, and stop the Pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sages through which it is to be voided.</p>
               <p>Finally, the fourth observation is concerning the use of the Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in general: to administer it with all the exactness possible, respect must be had unto the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Fits, unto their strength, unto the Accidents that attend them, unto the Temperature, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:59497:56"/>Age and Sex of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, unto the Season, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to other things, which though they might alter the manner of using it, ought not however to hinder the giving of it. For Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, in a very hot temper, in a tender Constitution, in a Child, and so forth; the Dose is to be lessened; it is then to be given in less Proportion, oftner, and continued longer; and if it be given with Wine it must be boil'd, or weakened by the Mixture of some convenient Liquor.</p>
               <p>After these General Observa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, we must expound after what manner this Remedy may be applied unto the Cure of all Fevers, and what the true and reasonable use of it ought to be. To perform which with the more
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:59497:56"/>Brevity, I will take for Example, <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>he manner of giving it in Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quors, and with Wine, which <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ay be easily extended unto all <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>he other Preparations.</p>
               <p>I begin with the Intermittent <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>evers, supposing that the Sick <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>re duly prepared, either by Bleeding, or by Purgation, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as there has been occasi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the one or the other; and having let some Accesses pass, to <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ry whether the Fever may not have been Cured with those ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>eral Remedies, or by Nature it <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>elf, which is always the best Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>hod: All these things being sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>osed, I say, in <hi>Tertian</hi> Agues, Use must be made of the Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>y at the end of a Fit. It is to <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e taken at divers Intervals till <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>he time of the next Fit, which
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:59497:57"/>does usually return, When that is over, the Remedy must be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated again in the same manner as before, till the time that ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Fit would be, if it were not prevented, and which ought not to return, if all that which has been said, is regularly observ'd.</p>
               <p>I do not terminate what Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals of time are to be observ'd betwixt each Dose of the Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; that depends on the strength of the Infusion, or on the length of the Intermission between each Fit: If the Infusion is strong,<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> longer space of time may be le<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> between each Dose than if it wer<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> weaker; and if the intermission is long, there is no necessity<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> multiplying the Doses as often, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> if the space of the Intermissio<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> was shorter. It suffices then t<gap reason="illegible: right margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:59497:57"/>give notice, that during the whole time of giving it, until the day that the Fit shall not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd, there ought to have been taken six drams, or one ounce of <hi>Quinquina,</hi> and sometimes more; that the Remedy must be given an hour or two before Meat, and two or three hours after; and that each Dose may be of four ounces of Liquor or thereabouts.</p>
               <p>To prevent the Return of the Ague, the Remedy ought to be continued during eight Days, two doses a day, in the Morning, and at Night before Supper, or going to Bed; and during eight days more, once a day, either Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or at Night.</p>
               <p>Use may be made during the last eight Days of a second Infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion made upon the Reliques of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:59497:58"/>the first, adding at pleasure a little of new <hi>Quinquina;</hi> or use may be made of the first Infusions, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving more Vertue, and being less ungrateful, only retrenching some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the quantity of the <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quina,</hi> with which there is no oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion of loading the Liquor so much with the Tincture thereof, as during the time of the Fits: Both ways are indifferent, except that there may be less Expences in one manner than in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>But if notwithstanding all those Precautions, the Fever should re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn (which is very rare, though, when all that I have said has been observ'd) the use of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy must be repeated again after the same manner as before, though not for so long time; and it will
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:59497:58"/>not fail however to produce the desired Effect, which is, to abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely prevent the Return; es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially if the Use of the Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is repeated immediately after the first Fit, and before that the Ague has made a new Progress.</p>
               <p>Moreover, it is not absolutely necessary then to observe a strict Diet during the Intervals of the Fits, especially if they are short and moderate; the Use of solid Food and of Wine may be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed also for the abovesaid reasons.</p>
               <p>There is no need of any other Rules than these for a Double <hi>Tertian.</hi> It is at the end of a Fit that the Remedy is to be given, and it must be continued as in the <hi>Tertian</hi> unto the Cure thereof, which commonly happens at the second Fit, or, at the latest, at the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:59497:59"/>third; observing only, that if the Fits are very long and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, the Use of Broths, and of Eggs is proper as to Nourishment: In all other respects, the same Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod as in <hi>Tertian</hi> Agues is to be observ'd.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Quartane</hi> and Double <hi>Quartane,</hi> require no new Rules neither. In the <hi>Quartane</hi> may be had all the time requisite to give the Remedy in, seeing that there are two whole days to give it in, without Interruption, after the same manner as in the former Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers; and the Fever is extinguish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed also at the third or fourth Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cess, if not at the very first, which very frequently happens. I say the same of the Double <hi>Quartanes;</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adding, that to prevent their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, the Use of the Remedy is
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:59497:59"/>to be longer continu'd after the Cure thereof, than after the Cure of the other Fevers. The reason is, that there being in those kind of Fevers, more of Acides in the Mass of Blood, there must be a longer time allowed to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, to correct and dissipate them; especially when that the Ague is obstinate and inveterate. I further add, that it is in those Agues above all others, that the most refreshing, and most hume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting Remedies are not the best; and that, on the contrary, Use may be made of Wine and of so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid Food, because that there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as I have said, more of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cides in the Humors to overcome, those kind of Aliments are more apt to be united unto the Action of the Remedy, to destroy more
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:59497:60"/>easily that predominant Sharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness.</p>
               <p>Moreover, the chiefest Obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations which are to be made in Intermittent Fevers, are, that the Remedy is to be given with such Circumspection that nothing may oppose its Action, but that on the contrary, all things may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute towards it. To this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, it were good to stay till the first Ebullitions of the Fermenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion were a little over and calm'd, especially when that the Fits are long and Violent; because, that otherwise the Remedy would not have time sufficient between the short Intervals, to impress its Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue unto the Mass of Blood, not Strength sufficient to overcome without resistance, the great E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bullition of the Humors: whereas,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:59497:60"/>if the Fermentation and the Fits were moderate from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Ague, to prevent the progress of the Leven, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy might be given with good Success, and even without any great Preparation. In such a Case, the Remedy has less of Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position to overcome, and it may more easily mortifie the Leven of the Fever, and blot out its first Impressions.</p>
               <p>Secondly, It must not be given at the beginning of a Fit, no more than during the time of it, because that that would excite a Combat, out of Season between the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy and that Leven, which is at that time in the vigor of its Action; and that it would unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarily fatigate the Sick. It is better then wholy to rely on Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture's
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:59497:61"/>Conduct, who labors to overcome, and to exhalate part of that Leven; but take that time to give the Remedy in which that Leven begins to act.</p>
               <p>Then does the Remedy inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept its Progress and even pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents it; and being convey'd unto the whole Mass of the Blood, by a more gentle Circulation, than that which is made in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue, it more easily, and with less resistance, imprints all its Vertue in it; it purifies it, and destroys the Fermentative Matter thereof, which would insensibly produce a new Fit.</p>
               <p>It is for the same reason also, that it may be taken in Liquor, rather than in a solid Substance, that it may pass with more ease every where; It is likewise giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:59497:61"/>at several times, to produce little by little the same Effect, and to gently and leisurely cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect that Vice which the Humors have contracted. There is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise but a small space of time allow'd betwixt each Dose, that the second Dose might uphold the Vertue of the first, the third that of the second, and so con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutively each other, least they might be over-weakened by too great a distance between each Dose. It is finally given very aptly two or three hours after Meals; because that within that time it unites it self with a part of the Chyle, which by that means enters, like a new Balsom, into the Mass of Blood, where it cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects and renews it.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:59497:62"/>
               <p>Through this manner of giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Quinquina,</hi> the Cure is not only certain, but even the time of it may be fore-told, see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that it is almost infallible that the Ague will not return at the time of its second Fit, reckoning from the beginning of the Use of the Remedy. And to make yet a more exact Prognostication, it is to be observ'd, that when the Ague is near its end, at that time, that Fit which follows the first Doses of the Remedy, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways different from that which has preceded the use thereof; it being sometimes longer, but most commonly shorter; that it comes at other hours than it did before; or that those Accidents that accompany it, are different from those of the other Fits:
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:59497:62"/>Then it may be said for certain, that that will be the last; or that that which will follow next, will be but like the Shadow of a Fit.</p>
               <p>Those Changes declare, that the Leven of the Ague is carried off by the Remedy, in lieu, that if they did not happen; or that they were but very moderate, that the Fit should return at the same hour as before, that it did last as long, and have the same Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents with it, it might be said, that the Remedy had not acted powerfully enough, and then it were requisite to augment its Strength, or to multiply its Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, to prevent the return of some Fits, which would however be very few in number, though there were no alteration made in the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:59497:63"/>use of the Remedy. It is here to be observ'd, that in the making of a very strong Infusion, or in the more frequent giving of it, there are some that are cured at the very first Fit, which causes a greater Admiration as to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy; but that does not produce a better or more certain Cure. It might rather be feared, that there were something too much forced in that Cure to last long; and that it were much better to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pease little by little the Fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Humors, and more insensibly communicate unto them the Vertue of this Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</p>
               <p>It is to be observ'd also, that if the Sick has a repugnancy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst so frequently taking of the Drink, it may be given less often,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:59497:63"/>as twice or thrice a day; provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that in each Dose there be the double quantity or therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts of the Infusion; those ways being but little different, and coming both to the same thing, they will produce the same Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</p>
               <p>Finally, It is to be observ'd, that if there should be an Ague so obstinate as not to yield unto the Remedy during divers Fits; and that it should always return at the same Periods, and after the same manner, which is very rare, it were requisite to leave off the Use of the Remedy du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring some days, and to give Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture some Reprieve, who may dislike a Remedy at some time, which it may approve of at ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, after which, the use of the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:59497:64"/>Remedy might be repeated again as before.</p>
               <p>It is certain, that continual Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers require more of Circumspe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction than the intermittent do; and that there are but few Rules in the giving this Remedy, that may be applied unto all Fevers indifferently. The divers Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances, and the different Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents which daily happen, do frequently oblige the hastening or retarding, or the suspention of the Use of the Remedy, of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering the manner of giving it, of joyning unto it, or of preferring unto it other Remedies. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, it belongs unto those Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitians that have joyned the Use of this Remedy unto the perfect Knowledge of the Disease to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine it: Mean time, it may be
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:59497:64"/>said in general, that part of those Rules which I have established as to intermittent Fevers, may be fitted unto Continual Fevers: It must be then, after Bleeding and Purgation, or after the Use of other Remedies. In a word, it must be after that the Sick has been well prepared, and that the greatest violence of the Fever has been suppressed, that this Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is to be given. There may be a Certainty that it will insen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibly appease the Fermentation of the Humors, and that it will cure the Continual Fevers as well as others. To that end it must be given at the greatest slacking of the Fever, in small Proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and in fewer Doses, if the Infusion be strong, more frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and in larger quantities, if
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:59497:65"/>the Infusion be weak, if it is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with Heat, if the Wine is mixed with some other conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Liquor; or if the Infusion is made but with a simple Pti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sane.</p>
               <p>Not but that the Infusion of the <hi>Quinquina</hi> may be given even at the beginning of a Continual Fever, provided that it be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any, or with very little Wine, and in several small Doses. In that manner, the Fermentation of the Humors is overcome, and its Progress prevented. Thus it has been oftentimes known, that divers Persons have been freed from Continual Fevers; the Cure of which, could not be reasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly attributed but to the use of a Ptisane of <hi>Quinquina,</hi> given for ordinary Drink during the whole time of the Fever.</p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:59497:65"/>
               <p>There yet remains something to be said as to the Use of this Remedy in Accidental Fevers. Experience has taught, that it quells likewise the Languid and Hectick Fevers; so that they be not too inveterate, or that they depend not on a considerable Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of some principal part: In such a Case there is little or no Remedy at all; nor is it to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, but in such as are in their Beginning, and that have yet some Relation with the other kind of Fevers, either by their periodical Returns, or by other Signs, which shew that the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver makes less Impressions on the Parts than on the Humors.</p>
               <p>In such a Case, the Remedy may be used much after the same manner as in the Continual Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:59497:66"/>and when that through those means the Fermentation is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peas'd, or at least very much aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted those Obstructions which cause those kind of Fevers will be the easier overcome. It is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so to be observ'd, as I have men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned it in the Intermittent Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, that if those Fevers are not easily overcome by the Remedy, in prudence, the Use of it is to be suspended during some days: Thus the Remedy being re-taken, after some time of rest, makes a greater Impression on the Leven of the Fever, and Nature ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers new Vigor to oppose it: Whereas, when the Remedy is made use of without Interrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Operation of it is relax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the Effect no longer so sensibly felt: Besides, through
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:59497:66"/>this Suspention some Rest is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded unto the Sick, who, in a long Fit of Sickness, is easily wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried and disgusted with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Use of the same Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</p>
               <p>In those Fevers which are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with a Discharge of Humor, on some Parts, it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that the Property of the Remedy being to prevent, and to resolve the Coagulation of the Humors, and to restore unto them their first Motion, it will disin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage part of the weight that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presses it; and will turn another way the Course of that which is carried thither; and at the same time, it will cause the Ebullition of the Humors to cease; or at least, will contribute very much towards it, with the help of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:59497:67"/>Remedies. Above all, the time of giving it, must be when that the Humors are yet in Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that they are not whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fixed on the parts: Also it is to be given at divers times, as in other Fevers.</p>
               <p>Finally, The same Remedy will not fail of producing its Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in malignant Fevers, where the Ferment is more eager and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute than in all others, as those accidents will manifest unto such Persons as reflect on them. It will blunt and correct the Sharpness of that Leven; and with the assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of Cordials, and of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Specificks, it will cause it to be breathed forth, or otherwise ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell'd, through such ways as Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture will appoint. To this end also, the Remedy is to be given
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:59497:67"/>at distinct times, especially when that the bad Leven, or that that which is most malignant in all the Mass of Blood, causes some E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions in the Skin, and in all the Habit of the Body. It is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary to add here, that to be more certain of the Cure, and to take away the Causes of Relap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, some Purgatives are to be used some few days after that the Fever is extinct. The Observa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that are to be made there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are, first, that it is fitting to have them joyned unto some Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations of the <hi>Quinquina,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause that thereby, at the time of the Purgation, the Vertue of the Remedy is communicated without Interruption. It is to be observ'd also, that the Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives are not to be of a very cool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:59497:68"/>Nature, no more than the Liquor in which they are given: They are not to be taken neither with too much Liquor, for fear of taking away, by those large Draughts, that Character of the Remedy which is imprinted in the Blood. It is likewise conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to give those Purgatives in small Doses, and more frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for some days together, or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very other day, to carry of lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surely the peccant Humors, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out prejudice to those which are impregnated with the Vertue of the Remedy.</p>
               <p>It is to be observ'd also, that frequently after the Cure of a Fever, there happens, during the Night, some Moisture and gentle Sweats, which shews, that through the action of the Remedy, the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:59497:68"/>Blood is more liquid and serous; or, if you will, more subtil, and more volatilized than its was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. In such a Case, such Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies are to be used as carry off, through other ways the superflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Serosities, and assist the Blood in returning into its Natural State.</p>
               <p>In general, those Purgatives that are to be used, are such as by their Bitterness, or other Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, have some Affinity with the <hi>Quinquina,</hi> to assist it, or at least, not to interrupt its Operation: As for Example, it may be with <hi>Rubarb, Aloes,</hi> or with the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract of <hi>Colloquintida;</hi> or with such as carry along with them the superfluous Serosities, as the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract or Rosin of <hi>Jalap</hi> and of <hi>Scamony,</hi> and the like; the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:59497:69"/>of which, as well as the manner of giving them, depend on the Conduct of the Physitian, and sometimes also on the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents Inclination.</p>
               <p>In the using of the other Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations of the <hi>Quinquina,</hi> as its Tincture, its Extract, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> there is no occasion of altering the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Method; they must always be used at divers times, and at such Intervals as are more or less long, according to the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of the <hi>Quinquina</hi> that is to be used; but in a weak Fever, in a good Habit, and in a good Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, it will suffice to give it five or six days together, once a day, in the time of the Intermission. The Tincture must be given every time by small or large Spoonfuls according to its strength; the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:59497:69"/>must be given by half drams, more or less, as it is to be repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more or less often; the Extract by Scruples. I'm so far from slight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Method, I prefer it in divers occasions, to others; especially, when that through some Natural Dispositions, the Patient has some repugnancy against Drinks; or that it cannot agree with his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish: and to say truth, it were to be wish'd, that in all other Occurrences, the same Success might be had in giving the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy less frequently, and in an easier manner. It is to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served also, that in Continual or in Intermittent Fevers, where the Fits are violent and long, and generally, when there is much of Heat, and of Driness in the parts, that the Drink is to be prefer'd
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:59497:70"/>to the Bolusses, and the Extracts, because that it is better distribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the Mass of Blood; and that by that Mixture the Heat of the Remedy (if it is at all to be feared) is weakened without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny loss of its Vertue.</p>
               <p>Finally, Both the Methods of giving the <hi>Quinquina,</hi> may be joyned together also, and given alternatively to the same Patient; sometimes in a Solid, sometimes in a Liquid Form, as it shall be judged sit. I determinate nothing upon that account; and I leave to every one the Freedom of keeping to that Method which pleases him best, and with which he has the best Success.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:59497:70"/>
               <head>Answers to some Objections against this Remedy.</head>
               <p>WHat I have now said of the Virtues of this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy would not be sufficient, if I did not answer also to such Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections as might, at first surprizal, raise some Scruples in the minds of those that have not yet a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Method of using the <hi>Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quina.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The first Objection may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sturb them more than the others; what will become of all the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Fevers? It may be said, seeing that the Remedy makes no sensible Evacuation, is it not to be feared that that matter should kindle again, and cause new Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders sometimes worse than the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:59497:71"/>first. It is fixed and precipitated for some time, it may be, but it is not evacuated, and what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains behind, is a Leven to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce new Fermentations; so that it is but an imperfect Cure, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Suspention of a Fever, which is apt to return; and that draws on other Distempers worse sometimes than the former.</p>
               <p>To answer to this, Reason and Experience are to be consulted: The First Reason will shew, that in all those that use this Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, after the manner that I have said, quite the contrary of what is feared, may be seen: For there will be but very few that will not be cured without return, or any other Accidents. The Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Reason will likewise strong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly support those Experiences. It
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:59497:71"/>is grounded on the Vertue of the Remedy, and the ordinary moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Nature; far from having some fixing or precipitating Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities that retain the Humors, it has such as are quite opposite, by which it ought to dissolve, and to dissipate the Leven of Fevers, as I have shew'd. And if I may say it, it appeases a Fermentation, by another that is quite contrary to that of Fevers; and by that new Agitation, which it commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicates to the Blood and the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, it opens also the Passages and Vessels, after which Nature does easily drive forth the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Leven, and the ill Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, by such ways as she best knows how to find; either by Stools, by Urines, or Sweats, or by Transpiration only, according
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:59497:72"/>as that Leven, or those Humors are more or less terrestrial and gross, or more or less running and fluid.</p>
               <p>The Example of those that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they are cured, continue for several. Nights in breathing Sweats, will suffice to prove what I say: For that clearly shews the dissolution and melting down of the Leven; and that by that means the Blood is more attenuated, and more volatilized, as I have said, which is an effect quite op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posite unto that pretended Ficti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Febrile matter.</p>
               <p>Add to that, if you would sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie those that are not satisfied without such evacuations as strike their outward Senses, that fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently there is not so much Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be evacuated as might be
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:59497:72"/>imagined; and that when the Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations of Humors are ceased, the greatest part of those Humors are tempered and rectified by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it self, which then turns them to a good Use. I will have no better Example of it, than that of divers persons, who not making use of any Remedies, are however, after violent Fits and Returns, perfectly cured, on a suddain, of the Fever, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any sensible Evacuation, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Art or by Nature, or without any Evil Consequences ensuing thereon.</p>
               <p>It may be further said against that Objection, that if the other Remedies that are usually em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed for the Cure of Fevers, do not fix the Humors as it is preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that this does: They have
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:59497:73"/>worse Effects when that they are too frequently repeated. The Strength is decayed, the Actions of the Stomach and of the other parts are weakened, the Digesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons remain imperfect, and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, there is a continual ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of bad Humors, which frequently maintain the Cause of Fevers more than they destroy it; whereas, applying one self to this Remedy, very frequently, at the very first all those Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies that are to be feared from the most part of other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies, are removed.</p>
               <p>It must not be said therefore, that in the Conclusion, it leaves ill Impressions, and causes dangerous Obstructions, which turn even unto incurable Dropsies; or that soon or late, one is sensible of the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:59497:73"/>bad Consequences of this Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice. For how can it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, that a Remedy that insen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibly destroys the Leven of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, and their evil Impressions, should, at the same time, retain so much as would supply Matter unto all those imaginary Diseases? This is an Accusation without Ground, and that could more justly be cast on divers other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies. To conclude then, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to Experience, which will shew unto all those that will make use of the <hi>Quinquina,</hi> with the necessary Method, and that will deal honestly, that one ought not to attribute unto it that which other Causes may have produc'd; but that the unruliness of the Sick may be taxed; or that it may be attributed unto recent
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:59497:74"/>Diseases, or unto the neglect of not preventing the Consequences which might have appeared af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the use of any other Remedy than this; and, it may be, with more Danger and Violence. This is what is to be prevented by all the other Aids of Physick also: For I intend not to play the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pirick here, who attributes all unto his Drug, who makes it serve for all Diseases, and that despi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses all other Things and Rules. I will not say neither, but that there may such Fevers be found, whose Accidents do sometimes compel the Physitians to employ divers other Remedies, both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and after this; or that there may not be some Fevers where this Remedy must not be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and where there is not some
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:59497:74"/>necessity to stick to the ordinary Remedies, without deviating from such general Rules as have been established from many Ages, and with so much reason, and which I have no thoughts of opposing by the use of this Remedy.</p>
               <p>The second Objection requires no less an Answer than the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. It will be urged, that the Remedy is hot, that it is always given in Wine; and that, in a word, it is adding Fire to Fire, and running hazard of increasing a Fever in lieu of diminishing of it.</p>
               <p>To answer to this Objection, I shall first say, that if Experience be consulted, it will be found, that all those Remedies which are put in use for the Cure of Fevers, and that are called Specificks, have
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:59497:75"/>as much, or more Degrees of heat than this: Yet it is not to be doubted, but that the Authors of those Remedies have founded their Experience on Reason it self; and that they have judged, that that Heat was necessary to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solve &amp; dissipate the Cause of the Fever; that even the Fever it self was instrumental therein, and made use of, by Nature, for the concocting of the matter of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers; that the best <hi>Crisis</hi> was the Transpiration, or Sweat, which is procured but through such Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies as are composed of subtil Parts, such as are penetrating and active, and consequently of hot qualities: And that Lastly, those Remedies that are moderately hot, enter in order to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction and Expulsion of the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brile
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:59497:75"/>Matter; whereas the refrige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating Remedies do very fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently suppress that perfect Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fervescency of the Humors, that insensibly conducts unto the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaporation and Dissipation of this Febrile Matter.</p>
               <p>It is to this purpose, that a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Ancient Author says very well, That the Heat being aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented by the Remedies, a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Ease, and a more suddain Cure is to be expected; and that sometimes it is the Learned Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitian's Prudence to increase even the Heat and the evil Ferment of the Fevers; because that if the Remedy cures not immediately the present Evil, yet he may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent that which is to come.</p>
               <p>But to apply those Reasons in particular unto the <hi>Quinquina,</hi> I
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:59497:76"/>have already said, that its Heat is more moderate than that of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers other Remedies: Its other Qualities, its bitterness, its rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, are likewise very temperate; and it is by those Qualities, which are called Second Qualities, that the first are judg'd of, which are Heat, Moisture, Driness, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And to speak yet more ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously one's Thoughts on that Quality of the Remedy, it suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth, be it what it will, that it extinguishes and resolves a Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whose Impressions upon the parts are more to be feared, than those that the Remedy it self would make. Mean time, it is so certain, that it makes no Impression of Heat, that Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples might be alleadg'd of such Persons as have not had any sence
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:59497:76"/>of Heat, after the taking of the <hi>Quinquina,</hi> during divers Months. The sole Example of the Cure of Fevers will suffice for all others; since that it cannot reasonably be said, that a Remedy, whose Essential Property is to extinguish a Fever, should increase a Heat, which is the Effect of the said Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
               <p>However, it is certain, that what other Remedies soever are us'd in the Cure of Fevers, they not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding do frequently last very long, that they give a strong Impression of Heat and Driness unto the Parts, and produce such troublesome Accidents as are but too well known.</p>
               <p>It may then be concluded from thence, that the true Remedy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Fevers, of what qualities
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:59497:77"/>soever they be, is that which can at once take away the Fermen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation that causes them, while that such Remedies as cure not always, though with Qualities seemingly contrary unto that strange Heat, are but accidental Remedies, that tend more to the Destruction of the Effects of Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation, than of Fermentation it self.</p>
               <p>But it may be, the Heat of the Wine with which it is given is more feared than the <hi>Quinquina</hi> it self. To which I answer, That not to mention the Sense of the most famous Ancient Authors, who, for the same Reasons which they did alleadg in the behalf of hot Remedies, did also prescribe Wine in all Fevers, even in the most ardent, and in those that
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:59497:77"/>were accompanied with the worst Accidents; I say, that without alleadging of their Authority, I shall only say, that that Wine which has only serv'd to extract the Tincture of the <hi>Quinquina</hi> has lost the greatest part of its strength: that it may be boyl'd or infus'd in Heat, to take off part of its Spirits; that it may be temper'd with some convenient Liquors; and finally, that the Remedy may be given in many other Liquors besides Wine. The <hi>Quinquina,</hi> as I have said, does sufficiently communicate its Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue to other Drinks, not to be unsuccessfully taken in the most simple and easiest manner that it can be given.</p>
               <p>Finally, It may be said, that the Fever is often apt to return,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:59497:78"/>which shews, that its Cause is not taken away by this Remedy. I know not whether those that will make that Objection, have given or taken of it after the manner that I have laid down; but I know, that without meeting with a very ill Disposition in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, or without those Errors which may be committed in giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Quinquina,</hi> the return of Fevers will be very rare. Those that will doubt of this for want of Experience, will yield, it may be, at the Reasons which I have given against the first Objection, where I have shew'd, that by that Remedy, the cause of the Fever is dissipated, and that its Leven is destroyed; especially, if a sufficient quantity of its Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, has penetrated the Mass of
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:59497:78"/>so that although there should be a return after some days, it might probably be said, that it were a new Ferment that produced a new Fever.</p>
               <p>It is not necessary to enter on the Particulars of those Failings or Errors that may cause Relap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses. I have already mentioned the most principal ones, which may be avoided by an Able Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitian, when he meets with an Obedient Patient. There is one yet which might not be thought on, if notice were not given of it; It depends on the Choice of the <hi>Quinquina;</hi> as it wants ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much that the <hi>Quinquina</hi> which is false and Bastard, should have the same Vertue as the right has; neither has it so certain an Effect, both as to the Cure, and to prevent the Returns.</p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:59497:79"/>
               <p>But let us suppose those Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapses, the worst that may happen: to be wholly freed from them, there needs but taking over again of the same Remedy, though in in a less quantity, and the Fever will return no more: For to be persuaded that a Fever that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens after some Months, is the Remnant of a former Fever, is putting the Cheat upon one's self. The Remedy taken during some time, has had leisure suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to destroy all the Ferment; and if there had been any left, those Changes which daily hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, and the continual floating of the Humors, which incessant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly move in the Bodie, would fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish the carrying off, or the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering of this Ferment; so that those Returns would proceed
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:59497:79"/>much less from the Reliques of the first Leven, than of those which should be newly produc'd through new occasions.</p>
               <p>Finally, though that the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver should return through some reliques of Leven, were it not better still that it should dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose it self into two Periods and leave unto the Sick some favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Intervals to recover his Strength, than to have no Rest during all the time that the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver does not yield unto all other Remedies? After all, do other Remedies exempt more from Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns; and are they of a more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sy and more certain use?</p>
               <p>These are the Objections which I thought would be made, I doubt not, but others may be yet imagined; but if before they
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:59497:80"/>be offer'd, a Tryal of this Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy be made, according to those Rules that I have already given; I am persuaded, that the good Success will prevent those Obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and will save the labour of proposing them. For my part, I have not made my Experiments so much upon reasoning, as I have grounded my reasoning on my Experience.</p>
               <p>This is what I had to say on the <hi>Quinquina</hi> in all Fevers. I could, it may be, assert by the same Reasons that I have advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in speaking of the Fermenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Fevers, that it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in general to destroy, or to hinder in part, such other Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentations as produce other Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stempers; and especially, those that depend on the excess of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:59497:80"/>Juices, which frequently predominate over all others, which extends far in Physick, seeing that divers Diseases have their rise from those evil Ferments. There needs no other Examples than the Hypocondriacal and Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterical Affections, which are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much known under the name of Vapors; in which Diseases, this is an excellent Remedy, as Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience has frequently shewn. I could place in the same Rank, divers Obstructions of the Spleen, Mesentery, and other parts, the suppressions of some Natural E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacuations, the Green Sickness, and some other Diseases that have some Relation with these; in which I have also had the Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of the good Effects of this Remedy; but let every one
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:59497:81"/>be convinced by his own Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience.</p>
               <p>It is however, easie to imagine, that though to this present time, the <hi>Quinquina</hi> has not been used but in Fevers, it may have been design'd by Nature unto other uses conducing to Health, of which no Tryal has yet been made; which yet might easily be done, seeing that there is no ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard in the use of a Remedy that has no hurtful Quality; and if that some Trial did confirm this Thought, it might be concluded, that the most part of Diseases un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which it would be proper, would differ less in their Causes than in their Effects, and that the Remedy would destroy Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation equally alike every where, which would produce
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:59497:81"/>different Effects, according to the Subjects that it would meet with: However, it might be as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serted by that which is already known to us of the <hi>Quinquina,</hi> that Nature has not produced a more excellent Remedy: if new Discoveries were not made as use<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful as these, on the Subject of such Remedies as might be used in other Diseases, we should not deserve those Reproaches, which Nature may so justly make us, of neglecting to seek after the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and Properties of her Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:59497:82"/>
            <head>Books Printed for, and sold by <hi>William Crook</hi> at the <hi>Green Dragon</hi> without <hi>Temple-Bar,</hi> 1681.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>BRevis Demonstratio,</hi> proving the truth and excellency of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Religion, demonstrated by reason, recommended to all rational persons by several eminent Divines in <hi>London, Twelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>An Answer to Mr.</hi> Ferguson<hi>'s Doctrine</hi> about Christs Justification and Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, with an Account of the ends and intents of Christs death and passion, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidered as a Ransom, by <hi>John Knowls, Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Primitive Institution,</hi> or a season<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Discourse of Catechism, wherein is shewed the Antiquity, necessity and benefits thereof, together with its suit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableness to heal the Distemper of the Church, by <hi>L. Addison,</hi> D. D. <hi>Twelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Sermon</hi> preached at the Funeral of a Sober Religious Man, found drowned
<pb facs="tcp:59497:82"/>in a pit, since revised and inlarged by the Author, upon the account of sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain death, <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Sermon</hi> preached at a Visitation in <hi>Chicester,</hi> by <hi>W. Howel.</hi> Quarto.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An excellent Rational Discourse</hi> of the Lawfulness of taking Use for Money, by Sir <hi>Robert Filmer;</hi> with a large Preface to it, by Sir <hi>Roger Twisden, Twelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Modest Plea for the Clergy,</hi> wherein is briefly considered their Original, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity and Necessity, together with the true and false grounds of their being so much slighted neglected, and unjustly despised, by <hi>L. A.</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Imitation of Christ,</hi> or the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Patern, written by <hi>Tho.</hi> à <hi>Kempis, twenty fours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Steps of Ascention unto God,</hi> or a Ladder to Heaven, being Meditations and Prayers for every day in the Week, and other occasions, by Dr. <hi>Gee, twenty fours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hugo Grotius</hi>'s <hi>Catechism</hi> in Greek, La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin and English, with a Praxis, <hi>octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:59497:83"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Spirit of Prophesie,</hi> a treatise to prove (by the ways formerly in use a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Jews in the Tryal of preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to a Prophetick Spirit) that Christ and his Apostles were Prophets. Toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the divine Authority of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Religion and the Holy Scriptures, the insufficiency of Humane Reason, and the reasonableness of the Christian Faith, hope and practice, deduced therefrom; and asserted against Mr. <hi>Hobbes,</hi> and the Treatise of <hi>Humane Reason;</hi> recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the Press by Dr. <hi>Gunning,</hi> Lord Bishop of <hi>Ely,</hi> by <hi>W. H. octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The King-Killing Doctrine of the Jesu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its,</hi> delivered in a plain and sincere Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course to the <hi>French</hi> King, concerning the re-establishment of the Jesuits in his Dominion: Written in <hi>French</hi> by a Learned Roman Catholick, now tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slated into English, and humbly present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the consideration of both Houses of Parliament, in <hi>quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Justifying Faith,</hi> or that Faith by which the Just do live, briefly descri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed;
<pb facs="tcp:59497:83"/>to which is added an abstract of some Letters about the excellency of the Common Prayer, against Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>octavo</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Sermon</hi> preached on the Fifth day of <hi>November,</hi> by Dr. <hi>G. Hascard,</hi> D. D. Rector of St. <hi>Clements Danes,</hi> and Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain in Ordinary to his Majesty, <hi>quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Sermon</hi> preached before Sir <hi>James Edwards,</hi> Lord Mayor of <hi>London,</hi> at the Election of Sir <hi>Robert Clayton</hi> to be Lord Mayor for the Year ensuing, by <hi>G. Hascard,</hi> D. D. and Chaplain in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary to his Majesty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Sermon</hi> preached before the Right Honourable Sir <hi>Robert Clayton,</hi> Lord Mayor of <hi>London,</hi> by <hi>Tho. Mannyngham,</hi> Fellow of New Colledge in <hi>Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Sermon</hi> preached at the <hi>Savoy,</hi> and published in <hi>French</hi> and <hi>English,</hi> by <hi>des Ecotais,</hi> new, <hi>twelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mercy Triumphant,</hi> being an Antidote against Dr. <hi>Lew. Du Moulin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Gardiners</hi> Epistle against <hi>Sandius,</hi> about Socinianism.</p>
            <p>These nine last are new.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:59497:84"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A Voyage into the Levant,</hi> by Sir H. <hi>Blount.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caesars Commentaries,</hi> with Mr. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds</hi> his observations upon them, in <hi>folio, Englished.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Thomas Herberts Travels,</hi> with Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, <hi>folio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A description of Candia,</hi> with an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Siege, and the surrender of it into the hands of the <hi>Turks, octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Calliope</hi>'s Cabinet, wherein all Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men may be informed how to order themselves for Feasts, Funerals, and all heroick meetings, to know all degrees of Honour, and how all degrees are to take place; with a Dictionary of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rald Terms, <hi>twelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A discourse of the Dukedom of</hi> Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, containing the original, antiquity, government, manners and qualities of the People: also the temperature of the Climate, the nature of the Air, <hi>&amp;c. quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The present State of the Jews,</hi> wherein is contained an exact account of their
<pb facs="tcp:59497:84"/>Customs, Secular and Religious; to which is added a discourse of the Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, Talmud and Gemara, by <hi>L. Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son.</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Travels of Ʋlysses,</hi> translated by <hi>Tho. Hobbes</hi> of <hi>Malmsbury, twelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Camera Regis,</hi> or the present State of <hi>London,</hi> containing the antiquity, fame, walls, river, bridg, gates, tower, officers, courts, customes, franchises, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of that City, by <hi>J. B.</hi> Esq; <hi>octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Circumcision of the great Turks Son,</hi> and the Ceremony of the Marriage of his Daughter, sent from the English Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bassador, <hi>folio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Scarron</hi>'s <hi>comical Romance,</hi> or a face<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious. History of a company of Stage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>players, interwoven with divers choice Novels, rare Adventures, and amorous Intrigues, written in French by Monsieur <hi>Scarron,</hi> and now done into English, <hi>fol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Wonders of the Peak in Darbyshire,</hi> in Latine and English, by <hi>Tho. Hobbes, octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:59497:85"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Parthenissa,</hi> a Romance, written by the Right Honourable the Earl of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rery, folio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clelia,</hi> an excellent new Romance compleat, in five parts, <hi>folio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All <hi>Homer's</hi> Works, translated into English by that great Master of the Greek and English Tongues, <hi>Thomas Hobbes</hi> of <hi>Malmbury, twelves.</hi> Together with the Authors life.</p>
            <p>A Chronicle of the late Intestine Wars in the three Kingdoms of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> by <hi>J. Heath</hi> Gent. with a continuation to the Year 1675. <hi>folio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The life and death of <hi>Mahomet,</hi> the Author of the Turkish Religion, being an account of his tribe, parents, birth, name, education, marriage, Filthiness of life, his Alcaron, first Proselytes, wars, doctrine, miracles, advancements, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by <hi>L. Addison,</hi> D. D. and one of his Majesties Chaplains in ordinary.</p>
            <p>A true declaration of the horrible Treasons by <hi>William Parry,</hi> Dr. of the
<pb facs="tcp:59497:85"/>Civil Laws, against Queen <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> his Tryal, Conviction and Execution for the same.</p>
            <p>The Historian's Guide, or <hi>England</hi>'s <hi>Remembrancer;</hi> being an account of the Actions, Exploits, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and other most remarkable passages in his Majesties Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, from the year 1600, to 1679. shewing the year, day and month each action was done.</p>
            <p>An Historical Narrative of Heresie, and the punishment thereof, by <hi>Tho. Hobbes</hi> of <hi>Malmsbury, folio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Hobbes</hi> his Life, written by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self in a Latin Poem, and now transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into English, <hi>folio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The same is in Latin in <hi>quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Institution of General History, or the History of the World, being a compleat Body thereof from the Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the World; wherein are descri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed the several Empires, and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporaries with them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Also the forms and models of Governments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> all in such unbroken order and method as yet never extant, by <hi>William Howel,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:59497:86"/>L. L. D. and now Chancellor of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> in <hi>folio,</hi> in 2 <hi>Vol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Historical Collections, or an exact ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the proceedings of the four last Parliaments (both Lords and Commons) of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> with the Speeches of several eminent Men in those Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh,</hi> Sir <hi>Fra. Bacon,</hi> Sir <hi>Ed. Hobby,</hi> Sir <hi>Fr. Moore,</hi> Sir <hi>Ed. Cook.</hi> Sir <hi>Jo. Crook,</hi> &amp;c. collected out of the Original Records, by <hi>Hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood Townsend</hi> Esq; a member in those Parliaments, <hi>folio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thomae Hobbs Angli. Malmsbur. Vita;</hi> being an exact account of Mr. <hi>Hobbes,</hi> of the Books he wrote, of the times when, and the occasions thereof; of the Books and Authors against him, of his Conversation and Acquaintance, being a full account of his whole Life, who died in the 97th. year of his Age, 8o.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Moors</hi> baffled; being a Discourse of <hi>Tangier,</hi> under the Earl of <hi>Teviot</hi>'s Government, <hi>quarto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Connexion, being choice Collections of the principal Matters in K. <hi>James</hi>'s Reign, 8<seg rend="sup">o</seg>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:59497:86"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>